{Tech Horse Domestication}
{Horse Domestication}
{Tech Horse Domestication Desc}
{Although mankind has long hunted wild horses for their meat, learning how to control and domesticate them brings many additional benefits. They can be raised as food animals, providing meat or milk, provide transportation, and assist with agriculture. However, early means of riding and harnessing them were crude, and additional developments are needed to unlock their true potential. Nevertheless, horse ownership is a symbol of wealth and power.}
{Tech Light Chariot}
{Light Chariot}
{Tech Light Chariot Desc}
{The chariot provides a massive leap forward in military capabilities, providing mobility that foot soldiers cannot match. It allows elite soldiers to quickly move to the crucial point in a battle, to wear heavier armor than would be feasible on foot, and to easily escape if necessary. An archer mounted in a chariot can pour arrows into an infantry formation with little fear of reprisal. 
The chariot is a complex piece of technology, requiring sophisticated wood bending techniques to create a cab and wheels and yoke that are both light and strong. The floor must be strong but flexible enough to cushion against bumps, the reigns must be long and strong. Only the richest and most powerful can maintain the team of skilled craftsmen needed to build a chariot.}
{Tech Heavy Chariot}
{Heavy Chariot}
{Tech Heavy Chariot Desc}
{With a larger cab, a heavy chariot can accommodate two warriors besides the driver. The extra man can provide additional firepower, or be armed with a long hafted melee weapon. The latter provides close in combat power in chariot vs chariot engagements, and allows mixing it up with infantry who've been suitably softened up by missile fire. Being mounted allows a warrior to wear heavier armor than would be feasible on foot.}
{Tech Four Horse Chariot}
{Four Horse Chariot}
{Tech Four Horse Chariot Desc}
{Adding two extra draft animals greatly eases the burden on the horses and reduces their fatigue. The ability to move at speed for longer, enhances effective combat power, and with more horse power, a more robust cab construction can be used, and the warriors can wear even heavier armor. }
{Tech Horse Riding}
{Horse Riding}
{Tech Horse Riding Desc}
{Early attempts at riding horses involved the rider sitting on the animals rump, which gave poor control and left the rider in a somewhat precarious position. The development of the bridle and bit, together with larger stronger horses, lead to the rider being able to sit in the middle of the back, giving much better control and balance.}
{Tech Horse Archery}
{Horse Archery}
{Tech Horse Archery Desc}
{An archer riding a horse enjoys many advantages in warfare. Against infantry or chariots, he can close to short range, dispatch a volley of projectiles, then retreat with little danger to himself, and the same technique can also be used against heavier less mobile cavalry. However, being able to accurately fire an arrow from a galloping horse requires great technique and much practice. Only nomadic tribes were able to field large numbers of horse archers with sufficient training. }
{Tech Stirrup}
{Stirrups}
{Tech Stirrup Desc}
{Stirrups are loops for a horse rider to place his feet in. They allow a rider a wider range of actions, particularly allowing them to stand and strike downwards powerfully. The development of stirrups and horse armor paved the way for battlefields all across Asia to be dominated by versatile cavalry armed with multiple weapons.}
{Tech Logographic Script}
{Logographic Script}
{Tech Logographic Script Desc}
{A logographic script is one where each symbol (or logograph) represents a single concept. In the earliest forms of writing, logographs were simple drawings of the things they represented. Over times, these drawings became simplified, stylized, and standardized into a common script. Intangible objects and concepts were often represented by symbols with similar sounds.}
{Tech Literature}
{Literature}
{Tech Literature Desc}
{The development of paper and an increasing literacy rate, lead to the development as reading as a form of entertainment. Legends, history and travel diaries were the first genres to become popular, but later a wide range of literature evolved including romance and humor. }
{Tech Literary Criticism}
{Literary Criticism}
{Tech Literary Criticism Desc}
{With the profusion of poetry and other literature, scholars find it useful to discus and compare the various works, to enumerate the various forms, and the most pleasing means to construct each. They also useful compare the merits of various works, and write notes to aid others in understanding and appreciating the most important works.}
{Tech Poetry}
{Poetry}
{Tech Poetry Desc}
{From the humblest village, to the imperial court, whether spoken, sung or chanted, a poem packs insight and emotion into a memorable verse. Although not all men are great poets, all gentlemen should be schooled in the art of writing poetry.}
{Tech Divination}
{Divination}
{Tech Divination Desc}
{Only Heaven knows the future, but it often sends signs of what is come. These signs may be in the passage of the seasons, the behavior of animals, or in the shape of clouds. One skilled in the art, can read the fate of a person in the shape of their face, or the lines in their palm.}
{Tech I Ching}
{I Ching}
{Tech I Ching Desc}
{Also known as the Book of Changes, the I Ching, is not a method to predict the future, but rather to bring the individual soul into closer alignment with the cosmos, and give a glimpse of its deeper workings. Yarrow stalks are used to create sequences of six lines, or hexagrams, and each of the 64 possible hexagrams has a meaning which the user should consider in relation to their question.}
{Tech Astrology}
{Astrology}
{Tech Astrology Desc}
{By a careful study of the stars, planets and other celestial bodies, the state of affairs in Heaven may be observed, and from that follow affairs on Earth. Thus, those skilled in the art are able to calculate the most auspicious times for major undertakings, determine whether couples are compatible in marriage, and to divine the character and fortune of a man from the state of Heaven at the moment of his birth.}
{Tech Oracle Bones}
{Oracle Bones}
{Tech Oracle Bones Desc}
{When a ruler is in doubt, he may wish to know the will of heaven. A shaman is summoned, and the requisite ceremonies performed, then the ruler's question is written onto a turtle shell, or ox bone, and a red hot stick touched to it. The Shaman can then interpret the resulting pattern of cracks to provide guidence to his king.}
{Tech Shamanism}
{Shamanism}
{Tech Shamanism Desc}
{The realms of men and spirits are separate,  but certain men and women are able see into the spirit world, and intercede with them on behalf of humanity. Through dances, ceremonies and sacrifices, they can summon rain, drive out demons causing sickness, appease angry spirits, and various other forms of useful magic.}
{Tech Priest King}
{Priest King}
{Tech Priest King Desc}
{The well being of the state depends on King performing the correct rites to honor his dead ancestors., Only the spirits of previous kings can  reach the spirit of the Yellow Emperor who can persuade Heaven to show favor to our state.}
{Tech Mandate of Heaven}
{Mandate of Heaven}
{Tech Mandate of Heaven Desc}
{An Emperor can only rule by the will of Heaven. If he has come to the throne, then this shows he has Heaven's mandate to rule. If he rules, virtuously, he will keep this mandate. If he does not, another Heaven will raise up another to replace him. If Heaven is displeased, it will send signs, floods, famines, earthquakes and other portents.}
{Tech Imperial Rites}
{Imperial Rites}
{Tech Imperial Rites Desc}
{The smooth functioning of the imperial court, and of society at large depend on correctly following the traditional rules for rituals, ceremonies and etiquette. The traditional rules foster respect to others, and force each person to acknowledge their correct place in the proceedings, and thus their own role and responsibilities.}
{Tech Ancestor Worship}
{Ancestor Worship}
{Tech Ancestor Worship Desc}
{It is the duty of the living to take care of the dead, lest their spirits be set adrift in heaven. If the spirits of the ancestors are well taken care of, they will intercede with the gods to improve the fortunes of the living.}
{Tech Daoism}
{Daoism}
{Tech Daoism Desc}
{The famous sage Lao Zi teaches his disciples to follow the Tao or Path. The Tao is the force behind all things, and adherents are urged to live in harmony with it, valuing simplicity and action through inaction. Alas these Taoists have a disdain for hierarchy and authority which can make them dangerous, though their straight forwardness and wisdom can make them valuable for smaller kingdoms.}
{Tech Confucianism}
{Confucianism}
{Tech Confucianism Desc}
{The sage Kong Zi advocates a society based on the duties of care and obedience between ruler and subjects, husbands and wives, parents and children, and older and younger siblings. Each person and should venerate their parents and ancestors, and know their place in society. Solemn rituals remind people of their place and duties. Such a system would bind a society together, and be suitable for the smallest village, or the largest empire.}
{Tech Book of Rites}
{Book of Rites}
{Tech Book of Rites Desc}
{Society thrrives when each person understands their place within it. Their place and duties are reinforced by ceremonies, rituals and the rules of social behavior. This book describes the form of these ceremonies, the rules of ettiquette, and the principles of piety and respect for others, as they have been passed down from the earliest times.}
{Tech Neo Confucianism}
{Neo Confucianism}
{Tech Neo Confucianism Desc}
{The scholar Zhou Dunyi has reinterpreted the ideas of classical Confucianism, and incorporated certain ideas from Taoism and Buddhism to create a rational system of morals and ethics. However, it rejects mysticism and holds that the Universe is fundamentally real, understandable by humans. It is each individuals responsibility to find a way to live in harmony with it, and with their fellow men.}
{Tech Buddhism}
{Buddhism}
{Tech Buddhism Desc}
{Although originating in India, many in China advocate the teachings of the Buddha. These are that life and all it contains are impermanent, and to achieve release from the cycle of birth and rebirth, people must realize this truth and detach themelves from earthly attachments. Meditation and high moral standards are the steps on this path.}
{Tech Mohism}
{Mohism}
{Tech Mohism Desc}
{The renowned engineer and thinker Mo Di advocates a society dedicated to improving the lives on all under Heaven. A benevolent ruler would guide his subjects, helped by a merit based bureacracy. Society would have a common moral code derived from logic, and people would care for each other, regardless of familial or other ties. He advocates the power of reason, frugality, and public service. Violence is to be abhored, but he recognies that a state needs a strong defense. An ambitious ruler would scorn these views, but they might provide strength and unity to a small beleaguered state.}
{Tech Legalism}
{Legalism}
{Tech Legalism Desc}
{Lord Shang believes that people will always act for their own benefit, and that a state should be organized so that people acting in their own interests, will also serve the interests of the state. Warfare and agriculture make a state strong, so a person's status should be determined by their performance in these areas. Traditional ranks and titles should be abolished. Strict laws and harsh punishments should preserve social order, and preserve a harmonious society.}
{Tech National Myth}
{National Myth}
{Tech National Myth Desc}
{Our people should learn the tales of their ancestors. Of the Yellow Emperor who taught their forebears to sow grain and wear clothes; of Yao and Shun who taught them how to live together in a strong state, and of Yu the Great who tamed the great floods, and brought prosperity to the land.}
{Tech Canon of Wisdom}
{Canon of Wisdom}
{Tech Canon of Wisdom Desc}
{The wisdom of our civilization is contained in the works of the great scholars and thinkers of old, the Four Books, and the Five Classics. Those who wish to enter the Imperial service should  acquaint themselves thoroughly with these works, so that they have a sound education in philosophy, ethics, history, poetry ritual and technology.}
{Tech History}
{History}
{Tech History Desc}
{Sometimes In the affairs of men, it seems that the wicked triumph, and the good perish, so if falls to the historian to record their deeds, that future generations shall know the truth, History clarifies right and wrong, and settles points which are uncertain. It calls good good, bad bad, honours the worthy, and condemns the unworthy. It preserves states which are lost and restores the memory of perished families. }
{Tech Tea Culture}
{Tea Culture}
{Tech Tea Culture Desc}
{Tea is one of the seven daily necessiteis of life. A simple drink enjoyed with family or friends. It may be drunk at home, or at fashionable tea houses, where scholars like to meet and discus idea. Offering tea may also be done as a mark of respect, apology or gratitude, and in these cases it should be carefully prepared and presented in equisite teapots and cups.}
{Tech Go}
{Wei Qi}
{Tech Go Desc}
{The origins of The Surrounding Game (also known as Go) are lost in history, but some claim it was invented by the sage king Yao to teach his son discipline and concentration. The game is played on a gridded board of 17 x 17 points (later 19 x 19) with player taking turns to lay black or white colored stones, which some say represent Yin and Yang. Although the rules are simple, the strategy is deep, and has been used by philosophers to illustrate many points of life. An appreciation of Wei Qi is a must for a well educated gentleman.}
{Tech Lineage Groups}
{Lineage Groups}
{Tech Lineage Groups Desc}
{A lineage is a set of people descended from a common ancestor. These descendants could band together to maintain a hall for the worship of common ancestors, and for mutual assistance. Some lineage groups had substantial property, and could provide loans, insurance, schools and political assistance to members.}
{Tech Bronze Making}
{Bronze Making}
{Tech Bronze Making Desc}
{Although mankind has long possessed the ability to make bronze, it has always been expensive and rare. This technology represents refinements of technique that allow for the more widespread use of bronze weapons and tools.}
{Tech Advanced Bronze Casting}
{Advanced Bronze Casting}
{Tech Advanced Bronze Casting Desc}
{Refinements in molding and pouring techniques enable the production of both more intricate items, and also for larger items. As well as better weapons, these techniques allow for the casting of large and elaborate ritual vessels that will impress friend and foe alike.}
{Tech High Tin Bronze}
{High Tin Bronze}
{Tech High Tin Bronze Desc}
{The qualities of bronze are determined by the quantities of copper and tin contained in it. Understanding the correct quantities for each use, creates superior weapons. Four parts copper to one of tin is best for axes, three to one for spears and halberds, two to one for knives and swords, and three to two for arrows.}
{Tech Iron Casting}
{Iron Casting}
{Tech Iron Casting Desc}
{The secret to extracting iron from its ore has long been known, but the resultant pig iron is largely useless. However, if it is reheated in a sufficiently hot furnace, molten cast iron can be produced, and cast into many useful items. While cast iron is neither as strong nor as attractive as bronze, it is much cheaper, and suitable for many agricultural implements, bells, and cauldrons.}
{Tech Malleable Cast Iron}
{Malleable Cast Iron}
{Tech Malleable Cast Iron Desc}
{Cast iron is too brittle for many applications, but it can be turned into a more malleable form by being heated for several days, and then slowly cooled. The resultant malleable cast iron can then be further worked by bending or stamping, greatly extending the range of objects for which iron is useful.}
{Tech Steel}
{Steel}
{Tech Steel Desc}
{If cast iron and wrought iron are melted together, the carbon content is correct to from steel. Repeated folding and hammering of the metal distributes the carbon uniformly yielding a metal of great strength, with the ability to hold a razor sharp edge.}
{Tech Hydraulic Bellows}
{Hydraulic Bellows}
{Tech Hydraulic Bellows Desc}
{The temperatures required to melt metal in a blast furnace can only be reached by supplying a constant flow of air via large bellows worked by men or oxen. However, with a suitable mechanism, they may be powered with a water wheel, greatly increasing the air supply, and thus the quantity of metal that may be melted.}
{Tech Coke Fuelled Furnace}
{Coke Fueled Furnace}
{Tech Coke Fuelled Furnace Desc}
{Traditionally, charcoal has been used to heat furnaces, but this is becoming harder to obtain as more forests are cut down. Coke is an alternative source of carbon, that is make by cooking coal in a hot airless kiln to drive off impurities. Since coke is also much stronger than charcoal, coke fueled furnaces can also be made larger.}
{Tech Sword Making}
{Sword Making}
{Tech Sword Making Desc}
{Small swords and daggers can be cast from bronze, but longer swords need to be made of steel or wrought iron. The so called "hundredfold refined steel" is used for swords of the highest quality. Lesser blades may use thirtyfold or fiftyfold refined steel. }
{Tech Variable Composition Sword}
{Variable Composition Sword}
{Tech Variable Composition Sword Desc}
{The ideal sword has very hard metal at the cutting edge, and a core of softer metal to give it flexibility and toughness. This can be achieved by combining different types of metal, or by applying differential heat treatments to the blade, using clay to allow some parts to heat or cool at different rates. Using these techniques, fine swords of surpassing effectiveness and beauty may be produced.}
{Tech Bronze Armor}
{Bronze Armor}
{Tech Bronze Armor Desc}
{While thick leather armor can provide good protection, bronze armor can be even better, and is less cumbersome. It is expensive, so only elite troops can be equipped with it, but it frees up leather workers to make armor for the rank and file.}
{Tech Lamellar Coat}
{Coat of Plates}
{Tech Lamellar Coat Desc}
{A coat of plates consists of many small plates of bronze or iron armor stitched or riveted together. Typically it takes the form of double faced armor, with chest back pieces supported by straps over the shoulder. It's cheap enough to produce that large armies can be equipped with it.}
{Tech Mountain Armor}
{Mountain Armor}
{Tech Mountain Armor Desc}
{This is the finest quality armor, affordable only to those of the highest rank. It consists of several layers of many overlapping small metal plates riveted together to provide protection that is both strong and flexible. The shape of these plates is similar to that of the character meaning "mountain", giving the armor its name.}
{Tech Horse Armor}
{Horse Armor}
{Tech Horse Armor Desc}
{The development of horse armor, and horses strong enough to wear it, greatly reduces a horses vulnerability in battle, particularly against soldiers on foot, and against arrows. The development of horse armor paved the way for cavalry to dominate the battlefield.}
{Tech Iron Armor}
{Iron Armor}
{Tech Iron Armor Desc}
{Although iron is not of itself superior to bronze as a material for constructing armor, it is much cheaper. This makes it feasible to for the rank file soldiers to be issued metal armor that protects most of their body. Tough steel can be used for breastplates and helmets used by the best protected troops.}
{Tech Bamboo Strips}
{Bamboo Strips}
{Tech Bamboo Strips Desc}
{Writing is more easily shared if written on a portable medium. Slips of wood or bamboo the length of a chopstick, and the width of two, are convenient for writing a column of twenty or so characters with a brush. Many such strips can be laced together with twine to form longer works.}
{Tech Paper}
{Paper}
{Tech Paper Desc}
{Paper is a most marvelous invention as a medium for writing. It is cheap to make, easy to write on, and light to carry. It is made by pounding rags or mulberry bark in water, until the individual fibers separate. They are then collected on a mat and dried. Many different materials such as hemp or sandalwood can be used to make paper of different types and qualities.}
{Tech Stone Rubbing Copying}
{Stone Rubbing Copying}
{Tech Stone Rubbing Copying Desc}
{Many important documents are inscribed in stone. It is useful to have copies of them on paper, but copying them is time consuming and error prone. A better technique is apply wet paper over the inscription, pushing it carefully into the engraved writing. Ink is then stippled onto the paper with a brush until it covers the whole surface. Since the ink does not cover the part pressed into the engraving, the characters can now stand out in white against the now blackened surface of the paper.}
{Tech Wood Block Printing}
{Wood Block Printing}
{Tech Wood Block Printing Desc}
{The most famous books are in great demand, but copying them is a labor intensive and error prone process. However, if the pages are carved in relief onto a wooden block, then the protruding writing can be inked, and the image transferred by placing a sheet of paper over it and rubbing the back of the paper firmly. In this way many true copies can be quickly and easily produced, and the works of the great scholars made available to all.}
{Tech Illustrated Books}
{Illustrated Books}
{Tech Illustrated Books Desc}
{In the same way that wood blocks can used to print characters, they can also be used to print simple diagrams and illustrations which make technical texts much easier to understand. Color illustrations can be made by using several differennt blocks, one for each color.}
{Tech Silk}
{Silk}
{Tech Silk Desc}
{Silk is a marvellous fabric, made from the cocoon of the silk worn moth. The cocoons must be gathered, and softened in hot water, then the strands of silk teased out and woven together. Very fine silks can be made from single strands, while many strands can be twisted into thread for rougher but stronger fabric.}
{Tech Textile Printing}
{Textile Printing}
{Tech Textile Printing Desc}
{Wooden blocks can be used to print patterns onto silk or other fabric, increasing its beauty and value. The pattern must be carved in relief onto the block, then ink or dye is applied to the raised part of the block, and the fabric rubbed firmly against it to transfer the pattern.}
{Tech Black Ceramics}
{Decorated Ceramics}
{Tech Black Ceramics Desc}
{Crude pots for everyday use can be produced by any village potter, but it takes a true craftsman to create more elaborate vessels, The highest quality wares have very thin walls, and are decorated in black or orange using paint or lacquer.}
{Tech Ceramic Roof Tiles}
{Ceramic Roof Tiles}
{Tech Ceramic Roof Tiles Desc}
{Glazed ceramic roof tiles look attractive, keep out the rain, and do not present the fire risk that thatched roofs do. A typical scheme involves alternating rows of flat and semi circular tiles, Different colored glazes are used to designate different types of buildings, with yellow being reserved for imperial buildings.}
{Tech Tricolor Ceramics}
{Tricolor Ceramics}
{Tech Tricolor Ceramics Desc}
{Exuberant multi-colored decorative ceramic figures in yellow, green and brown, can be created by adding metal oxides added to the glaze, that change color depending on the time they are fired for. Popular subjects are horses, camels, soldiers and dancers. Such wares are popular as funery objects.}
{Tech Industrial Pottery Production}
{Industrial Pottery Production}
{Tech Industrial Pottery Production Desc}
{The demand for earthenware can only be met by streamlining the production process. Teams of potters make the basic pots, decorators add glaze and other decorations, before the vessels are sent to be fired in massive kilns. Skilled painters add the finishing touches to those pieces that need it.}
{Tech Porcelain}
{Porcelain}
{Tech Porcelain Desc}
{Made from fine Kaolin clay porcelain is renowned for its pure white color, hardness, and translucency. The most famous style known as "Qinghua" is decorated with blue glaze, and fetches high prices around the world. Different kilns around the country have established their own different styles leading to a great variety of wares. Another famous style is "Celedon" which has a pale greenish or blueish color.}
{Tech Iron  Plough}
{Iron  Plough}
{Tech Iron  Plough Desc}
{Ploughing is a process of turning over the top layers of soil prior to planting seeds. It brings fresh nutrients to the surface, and buries weeds. A sturdy iron plough has a vee shaped blade to cut the soil and wings to turn it over. Cheap cast iron ploughs are affordable for the humblest peasant farm, and significantly increase crop yield.}
{Tech Zither}
{Guzheng }
{Tech Zither Desc}
{The guzheng is a large stringed instrument with sixteen or more strings, and movable bridges. A sound board of wutong wood provides resonance. Players use both hands, and often use picks of shell or ivory attached to the fingers of the right hand. The instrument can produce tremolo, vibrato and cascading sounds reminiscent of thunder, waterfalls, or galloping horses. Strings can be made of animal gut, silk, or steel.}
{Tech Theatre}
{Theater}
{Tech Theatre Desc}
{One of the hundred entertainments that everyone can enjoy, theater performances employ a chorus to tell the story, while actors depict the events with mime and dance. Male actors often perform dramatic moves derived from martial arts, while female performers dance in long dresses with ribbons and long fluttering sleeves.}
{Tech Opera}
{Opera}
{Tech Opera Desc}
{The Chinese Opera is an evolution of previous theatrical styles. Performers wear elaborate make-up to show their role in sophisticated plays. They sing, recite and play musical instruments, while an orchestra provides rhythmic backing. Clowns may lighten the mood. Performers are known as disciples of the pear garden, after the first troupe established at the imperial court.}
{Tech Calligraphy}
{Calligraphy}
{Tech Calligraphy Desc}
{The art to be prized above all others. The pursuit of a true gentleman. The simple strokes made with brush and ink are much more than a way to memorize the characters, they are an embodiment of life. The brush becomes an extension of the writer's arm, and the strokes reveal his character, his impulsiveness, restraint, elegance, and rebelliousness. }
{Tech Painting}
{Painting}
{Tech Painting Desc}
{Painting used for illustration is a mere trade performed by artisans, but certain gentlemen elevate it to an art form. The greatest works are studies of plants or animals, with the subject depicted in exquisite detail, while the background is often left indistinct. Some prefer to paint with color, others emphasize form by restricting themselves to simple black strokes.}
{Tech Precious Metal Work}
{Precious Metal Work}
{Tech Precious Metal Work Desc}
{The art of gold working is associated with the barbarians to the North. They excel at making fine object depicting real or mythical animals, often as broaches, buckles or amulets. Possesion of such fine works in silver or gold shows the power and status of the owner.}
{Tech Jade Working}
{Jade Working}
{Tech Jade Working Desc}
{Jade has always had a special place in Eastern culture. The stone is said to posses many virtues, for instance its ability to take an edge but not be sharp is said to represent justice,  and the flaws within revealed by its translucency represent sincerity. The very hard raw stone can be shaped by abrasive means into a variety of  beautiful ornamental and ceremonial objects. Quality objects shaped by a master craftsman are more valuable than gold. }
{Tech Coinage}
{Coinage}
{Tech Coinage Desc}
{The earliest medium of exchange was cowry shells, but round coins made from copper, bronze or iron proved a more practical type of money. Chinese coins had holes in the center allowing them to be strung together into groups of 100 or 1000, and carried over the shoulder. The development of coinage will facilitate the development of trade and allow a greater range of government taxation measures.}
{Tech Paper Currency}
{Paper Currency}
{Tech Paper Currency Desc}
{As the economy developed, vast quantities of coins were required, with 6 billion being minted in one year, and shortage of metal often lead to debasement of the currency. Coins were also bulky and heavy, with a string of 1000 weighing several kilograms. The development of paper money makes larger transactions more convenient and allows further expansion of trade.}
{Tech Joint Stock Company}
{Joint Stock Company}
{Tech Joint Stock Company Desc}
{The concept of a joint stock company allows individuals to band together to undertake ventures that would be too large or risky for one alone. They also allow the separation of ownership and management allowing wealthy merchants to participate in many ventures simultaneously. Since a high degree of trust is needed between the owners, companies were often formed by members of the same lineage group.}
{Tech Banking}
{Banking}
{Tech Banking Desc}
{A sophisticated economy, requires services for the deposit of cash, issue of letters of credit, and for loans for various ventures. These services can be provided by wealthy merchants and companies, and their availability will further boost trade.}
{Tech Cannon Making}
{Cannon Making}
{Tech Cannon Making Desc}
{Cannons may made of bronze or even wood, but most are made of iron. The barrel must be exceedingly strong to withstand the blast of the gunpowder, and so must have an even thickness and no flaws. A barrel's strength may be enhanced by wrapping it in metal bands. Repeated hits from cannon balls will cause any masonry to quickly crumble, so cannon can quickly breach even the strongest city walls.}
{Tech Hundred Tigers Launcher}
{100 Tigers Rocket Launcher}
{Tech Hundred Tigers Launcher Desc}
{By mounting many small rockets in a rack attached to a wheelbarrow, a device can be fashioned that can launch a fearsome barrage of rockets in a short time. The rockets may be wildly inaccurate, but this will just spread the fear more widely throughout the enemy force.}
{Tech Triple Giant Crossbow}
{Triple Giant Crossbow}
{Tech Triple Giant Crossbow Desc}
{Mounting three large crossbows together to fire a single three meter long bolt, creates a weapon of surpassing range and accuracy. The enemy can never feel safe from it, even if many hundreds of meters distance, and no armor can protect against its bolts. Indeed one bolt may pierce through several men if they are standing close together.}
{Tech Giant Crossbow}
{Giant Crossbow}
{Tech Giant Crossbow Desc}
{Crossbows too large for a man to carry can be mounted on special carts. They can fire long bolts over great distances, easily piercing any armor and likely killing any man or horse struck by them.}
{Tech Counterweight Trebuchet}
{Counterweight Trebuchet}
{Tech Counterweight Trebuchet Desc}
{While rope pulled trebuchets can fire large projectiles over great distances, their shots are somewhat wayward, never striking the same place twice. The Muslims to the West have invented a superior machine, in which men winch a large box of stones or earth into the air. It is then suddenly dropped, sending the projectile flying. The force generated is more predictable, allowing the machine to consitently strike the same spot, crumbling the target wall more quickly.}
{Tech Four Legged Engine}
{Four Legged Engine}
{Tech Four Legged Engine Desc}
{To throw the large rocks required to break down the strongest city walls, a very large engine is required. The four footed engine is a tall engine comprising four large upright breams cross braced for strength. The throwing arm is long and thick, and large crew of rope pullers provide the power. It can breach any type of wall.}
{Tech Crouching Tiger}
{Crouching Tiger}
{Tech Crouching Tiger Desc}
{The Crouching Tiger is a sturdy form of stone throwing engine, capable of breaking down rammed earth walls. Two sturdy upright triangular frames support the pivot bar, and cross bracing makes the machine strong and stable. The throwing arm may be made from several bamboo poles, so that it is strong enough to throw larger rocks. }
{Tech Stone Throwing Engine}
{Stone Throwing Engine}
{Tech Stone Throwing Engine Desc}
{An engine can be devised to throw rocks and stones over long distances. It can be used to bombard enemy soldiers, or to break down light fortifications. It uses a long bamboo pole balanced on a supporting frame. One end is placed on the ground with a sling or basket to contain a rock to be thrown, while the other end is supported high in the air by the frame. Men pull down on ropes attached to the high end, causing the low end to pivot up and fling the rocks.}
{Tech Rammed Earth Wall}
{Rammed Earth Wall}
{Tech Rammed Earth Wall Desc}
{The sticky yellow earth of China can be placed in a frame and repeatedly pounded with a special stick until it becomes extremely hard. While there is some technique in this, the real challenge is to organize the thousands of workers needed to create a suitable wall around a large city.}
{Tech High Walls}
{Improved Wall Construction}
{Tech High Walls Desc}
{By improving the techniques of construction, attention to foundations, organization or works crews etc, it is possible to construct fortifications of imposing height, and great thickness. Historically, major cities had walls up to 20 m high, with a width even greater.}
{Tech Brick Faced Walls}
{Brick Faced Walls}
{Tech Brick Faced Walls Desc}
{While earthen walls can be high and strong, they are susceptible to damage by flooding, erosion by wind and rain, and being worn down by missile attacks. Facing the walls with brick protects against all these dangers, and makes the appearance of the wall look more imposing. Upon completing this development, all your earthen walls will be upgraded automatically.}
{Tech Military Architecture}
{Military Architecture}
{Tech Military Architecture Desc}
{While a city wall makes it difficult for an enemy to attack, an enemy left undisturbed will find ways to breach or scale it. It's therefore necessary to build structures atop the wall that allow defenders to rain down fire on those approaching the wall, and to disrupt enemy operations.}
{Tech Agriculture}
{Agriculture}
{Tech Agriculture Desc}
{Although the methods of planting cereal crops have been known to many for thousands of years, not all societies have yet adopted a settled farming lifestyle, preferring instead to rely on hunting, gathering or maintaining large flocks of animals. Agriculture allows better use of land that is sufficiently fertile, but also requires more labor.}
{Tech Pastoralism}
{Pastoralism}
{Tech Pastoralism Desc}
{Pastoralists rely on their large flocks of animals to provide them with food. The number of flocks that can be kept is mainly limited by the quantity and quality of land available. A pastoral lifestyle requires far more land to sustain a given population than an agricultural one, and cannot sustain large settlements. It does however allow survival in areas unsuited to agriculture.}
{Tech Nomadism}
{Nomadism}
{Tech Nomadism Desc}
{Flocks need to spread out to find grazing, but the need to keep track of them limits the area that any settlement can make use of. Using horses enables flocks to be controlled over a much wider area, and increasing the amount of land a settlement may use. It also makes it easy for groups to split off to new locations, so this development allows settler units to be recruited at zero cost.}
{Tech Flood Control}
{Flood Control}
{Tech Flood Control Desc}
{Left to their own devices, rivers are capricious, often flooding and changing course suddenly causing massive disruption to agriculture. Dredging their channels and building levees to control their flow makes them a little more predictable, and allows agriculture to be more permanently established.}
{Tech Irrigation}
{Irrigation}
{Tech Irrigation Desc}
{Crops need water to grow, and the supply from rainwater can be unpredictable. Creating a system of channels to distribute water from rivers or bore holes ensures that crops are well watered all year round, whatever the whims of the rain gods.}
{Tech Terracing}
{Terracing}
{Tech Terracing Desc}
{It's difficult to farm hillsides with cereal crops, as water runs off. Converting the slope to a series of stepped terraces provides flat land for cultivation, and allows water to be retained. Generally some method of pumping water up the hillside to the terraces will also be required. }
{Tech Marsh Drainage}
{Marsh Drainage}
{Tech Marsh Drainage Desc}
{Much otherwise useful flat land is too water logged to allow farming or grazing. Although it is very labor intensive, it is possible to construct drainage works to control water flow into and out of a marsh, and thus convert it into a fertile plain that can be farmed or used for grazing flocks.}
{Tech Seedling Transplantation}
{Seedling Transplantation}
{Tech Seedling Transplantation Desc}
{Crop yields for rice can be improved significantly if rice plants are grown from seeds in a nursery area for two to three weeks, before being transplanted to the main field. The small plants in the nursery are easy to care for, and when transplanted, they have a head start over any weeds that would compete with them. Transplanting also allows the part grown plants to be evenly spaced, further increasing yield.}
{Tech Brick Faced Wells}
{Brick Faced Wells}
{Tech Brick Faced Wells Desc}
{The climate is often dry, and it is necessary to draw up water from wells to water the crops, and provide for people and animals. While wells can be dug easily, they collapse quickly if not well lined. A lining of trapezoidal shaped bricks (smaller on the inside than the outside) is easy to lay, and will keep the well open permanently.}
{Tech Crop Rotation}
{Crop Rotation}
{Tech Crop Rotation Desc}
{The five sacred grains that have been grown from ancient times are millet, wheat, rice, soya beans, and sesame. They may be grown at different times of the year, or in different climates. It is better if they are not grown in the same spot each year, as this leads to depletion of the soil, and a build up of weeds and pests. Rotating the different crops between different fields significantly increases the yield.}
{Tech Composite Bow}
{Composite Bow}
{Tech Composite Bow Desc}
{Unlike a simple bow, a composite bow is made of multiple materials, wood, sinew or horn, glued together. Using different materials on inner and outer edges allows it to bend further, allowing construction of bows that are powerful without being unduly large.}
{Tech Crossbow}
{Crossbow}
{Tech Crossbow Desc}
{It takes years of practice to make a good archer, but new recruits can be trained quickly to use a crossbow. While it's rate of fire is slower, this is offset by the crossbow's superior killing power and armor penetration. The secret to making a crossbow is the sophisticated bronze trigger mechanism.}
{Tech Chu ko nu}
{Chu Ko Nu}
{Tech Chu ko nu Desc}
{The Chu ko no is a repreating crossbow, particularly favored by peasants. The string is pulled back by hand, so each shot is rather weak, but the recocking motion loads another bolt, allowing a shot to be fired off every couple of seconds. It can be effective against unarmoured targets, but against armored troops, its effect is more disconcerting than lethal. Sometimes the bolts are tipped with poision to increase their effect.}
{Tech Flaming Pitch}
{Flaming Pitch}
{Tech Flaming Pitch Desc}
{Pitch is a sticky flammable substance that can be extracted from wood, or found naturally in tar pits. It can be used to coat arrows or boulders. It allows artillery engines to fire flaming rocks, and improves the effectiveness of infantry flaming arrows.}
{Tech Gunpowder}
{Gunpowder}
{Tech Gunpowder Desc}
{Alchemists searching for an elixir of immortality have chanced upon a most useful "fire medicine" that burns extremely fiercely, even explosively in some compounds. Bundles of the  powder can be attached to arrows to provide much more effective incendiaries than was previously possible.}
{Tech Beehive Rocket Launcher}
{Beehive Rocket Launcher}
{Tech Beehive Rocket Launcher Desc}
{Experiments with gunpowder have shown that burning powder alone is enough to shoot an arrow through the air without the need for a bow. There rockets are light so a single man may carry many in a bundle and launch them like a swarm of angry bees. Although rather inaccurate, they will cause great fear amongst the enemy, and not a little damage.}
{Tech Thunderclap Bomb}
{Thunderclap Bomb}
{Tech Thunderclap Bomb Desc}
{By filling an earthenware pot with gunpowder, a most effective projectile can be fashioned for engines to throw, that will explode on impact, affecting enemy over a wide area. Sharp spikes of iron, or shards of pottery contained within the top will cause a shower of deadly shrapnel further enhancing the deadly effect.}
{Tech Three Eyed Gun}
{Three Eyed Gun}
{Tech Three Eyed Gun Desc}
{If gunpowder is confined in a closed tube, and a lead ball that fills the tube completely placed atop it, the ball will be expelled with great force when the gunpowder explodes. The range of the ball is short, but it strikes with a lethal force far greater than any arrow. Three such tubes can be attached to a handle to create the three eyed gun.}
{Tech Hot Cold Theory}
{Hot Cold Theory}
{Tech Hot Cold Theory Desc}
{Good health depends on maintaining the internal Qi balance between the major organs. Different foods affect different organs, and may also be divided into hot and cold types depending on their overall effect. Cold foods include fruits, vegetables and grains, whereas salty or fried foods are considered hot.}
{Tech Medicine}
{Medicine}
{Tech Medicine Desc}
{The role of medicine to restore balance to the body and enable it to recover from illness or injury itself. The practitioner examines the patient, determines where the imbalances lay, and then prescribes medication to rectify it. Over time a vast body of knowledge has been built up about the qualities of different plants, herbs and animal parts.}
{Tech Acupunture}
{Acupuncture}
{Tech Acupunture Desc}
{The effective functioning of a body depends on the flow of Qi (energy) through a set of meridians. If the flow of Qi is disrupted, illness or chronic disease may result. The flow of Qi may be manipulated and restored by the insertion of fine acupuncture needles at specific locations on the body.}
{Tech Anesthetic}
{Anesthetic}
{Tech Anesthetic Desc}
{Certain herbs, particularly the mandrake plant can be used to render a person unconscious. Bandits may use them to rob their victims, but they also have great benefits in medicine, allowing doctors to easily perform operations that would otherwise be difficult due the great pain caused to their patients.}
{Tech Blood Circulation}
{Blood Circulation}
{Tech Blood Circulation Desc}
{It has long been understood that in the same way that Qi circulates through the meridians, blood also circulates through the body. Understanding the details of this process is most beneficial to the treatment of illness and injury.}
{Tech Yin and Yang}
{Yin and Yang}
{Tech Yin and Yang Desc}
{Yang is the light, Yin is the shade. Without one, there cannot be the other. Yang and yin are the opposing but complementary forces that permeate nature. Hot and cold, life and death, fire and water, action and passivity, male and female. These ideas underpin most of Chinese thought.}
{Tech Massage}
{Massage}
{Tech Massage Desc}
{The flow of Qi and blood through the body may be stimulated and improved by expert manipulation of the limbs, pressuring of the muscles, promoting good health and providing relief from pain and weariness.}
{Tech The Five Elements}
{The Five Elements}
{Tech The Five Elements Desc}
{Wood, Fire, Water, Earth and Metal are the five elements. They are the five phases, the five agents, the five processes, the five steps. Each overcomes the other in a great cycle. This progression can explain the movements of the cosmos, the interaction of bodily organs, and the rise and fall of political regimes. Green, red, black, yellow and white are their colors.}
{Tech Tai Chi}
{Tai Chi}
{Tech Tai Chi Desc}
{This combination of movement, breathing and mediation can train both the body and spirit. Its practice promotes health, balance, calmness and awareness. Often movements are performed slowly, and faster movements may be performed as a form of martial art.}
{Tech Kung Fu}
{Kung Fu}
{Tech Kung Fu Desc}
{There are many different styles of fighting. Some mimic the styles of animals, some emphasize speed and fluidity, other stability and strength. To master any of these, both the body and mind must be trained. The basic stances must be learned, breathing mastered and the mind cleared, to allow the student to focus his Qi.}
{Tech Military Drill}
{Military Drill}
{Tech Military Drill Desc}
{Moving a group of men in close formation requires special techniques to maneuver and maintain formation. The ability to do this provides an impressive spectacle, and enables the creation of new types of military units.}
{Tech Signaling}
{Signaling}
{Tech Signaling Desc}
{An army is of no use if it cannot be commanded. The use of drums and flags to signal instructions will lead to a new type of more responsive and controllable military force.}
{Tech Combined Arms}
{Combined Arms}
{Tech Combined Arms Desc}
{A successful force usually combines both missile and melee troops. However, using them together correctly can be difficult. Co-operation can be made easier by combining the two types into multi-purpose units.}
{Tech Military Theory}
{Military Theory}
{Tech Military Theory Desc}
{As some scholars have studied the laws of nature, or pondered the minds of men, others have begun to make a systematic study of the practices of successful military commanders, and to compose books on the art of war. Any commander who wishes to be well prepared should be familiar with them.}
{Tech Calendar}
{Calendar}
{Tech Calendar Desc}
{The movement of the moon and stars mark the passage of time. By careful study of these, a calendar may be devised to divide time into years and months, and to determine when is the correct time to plant and harvest crops. Sadly the months marked by the phases of the moon, do not divide evenly into the year, so some years will have 12 months, and some 13.}
{Tech Astronomy}
{Astronomy}
{Tech Astronomy Desc}
{Careful observation of the of movements of the sun, moon, comets and other celestial bodies, reveals many patterns. In particular it reveals that events such as eclipses and the appearance of comets may be predicted. Foretelling these events will prevent panic, and greatly enhance the prestige of the ruler.}
{Tech Mathematics}
{Mathematics}
{Tech Mathematics Desc}
{Understanding the properties of numbers and shapes, and how to calculate them is of great benefit in many fields. In can assist in problems of astronomy, architecture, surveying and taxation among others. An educated gentlemen should be acquainted with all the principles of mathematics.}
{Tech Abacus}
{Abacus}
{Tech Abacus Desc}
{An abacus is a most marvelous device for aiding calculation. It consists of columns of beads in a frame divided into two parts. Most commonly, each column has two beads in the upper part, and four in the lower. Numbers are added by moving up beads in the lower part, until all are used when a bead in the upper part is moved. When the upper beads have both been moved, that column is reset, and a bead in the next column moved.}
{Tech Road Building}
{Road Building}
{Tech Road Building Desc}
{Construction of easily passable roadways will improve trade and speed the movement of military forces. The road bed needs to be compacted and levelled, then a layer of small stones added to provide drainage, and finally large stones laid on top to provide a smooth surface for carriages and chariots. Walls, signposts and guard houses should be placed along the road, and staging posts established to provide fresh horses for government officials.}
{Tech Churn Drill}
{Churn Drill}
{Tech Churn Drill Desc}
{Deep holes can be bored by placing a bit made of a heavy wooden log with a sharpened tip on one end into the ground, and then repeatedly raising and dropping a heavy weight onto the other end. Larger shafts can be bored using teams of oxen to rotate the bit, while water is poured into the bore hole to wash out the crushed rock.}
{Tech Mine Ventilation}
{Mine Ventilation}
{Tech Mine Ventilation Desc}
{Mining deep under the ground presents two main problems, how to remove ground water, and how to provide fresh air to the miners. Water can be removed with a chain pump, and air circulation can be achieved by using several carefully placed shafts. By this meathod it is possible to mine as far as 60 metres under the ground.}
{Tech Five Punishments}
{The Five Punishments}
{Tech Five Punishments Desc}
{Establishing a clear set of laws and punishments for transgression will enable a more harmonious society where everyone knows to expect severe punishment if they violate the laws. Magistrates should be appointed to  assess cases, and assign a punishment of a severity suitable for the crime committed. The five punishments shall be tattooing on the face, mutilation or amputation of different body parts, and death.}
{Tech Equal Temperament Scale}
{Equal Temperament  Scale}
{Tech Equal Temperament Scale Desc}
{Musical notes sound the most pleasant when the frequency of each is some fixed multiple of the one below it. If a note is double the frequencey of another, they are separated by one octave. Practical music requires the octave to be divided into a number of semitones, twelve being the most common, with the frequency of each note being a fixed ratio to the one below. This has long been recognized, but tuning instruments to this scheme has always involved much trial and error. Now there is a firm mathematical formula for how to do this.}
{Tech Ship Building}
{Ship Building}
{Tech Ship Building Desc}
{Constructing larger vessels that can transport armies, and cover great distances, requires mastery of many skills The shipwright must draw up a design that is light, yet strong enough to support its weight. Craftsman must cut wooden pieces accurately according to the design before they are assembled. Iron nails are needed to fasten the planks together, and caulking to make the ship watertight. Finally, oar mounts and rowing techniques must be developed for vessels where the rowers sit well above the waterline.}
{Tech Watertight Compartments}
{Watertight Compartments}
{Tech Watertight Compartments Desc}
{If watertight transverse bulkheads are placed across a ships hull, it is divided into multiple compartments. If one compartment is holed or leaks, the ship will not sink, and water from leaks can more easily be pumped out. Providing pluggable holes between compartments allows water to be drained from one to the other, improving ship balance, and further facilitating pumping.}
{Tech Junk Sails}
{Junk Sails}
{Tech Junk Sails Desc}
{The junk is a design of seagoing ship with a shallow draft, and a high poop. Its most noticeable feature is the sails, which are divided by a number of wooden battens. Ropes attached to the battens allow sail to be taken in or let out according to the conditions, and prevent tears in the sail from spreading. They also keep the sail flat and aerodynamically efficient.}
{Tech Stern Rudder}
{Stern Rudder}
{Tech Stern Rudder Desc}
{Small ships can be steered with an oar mounted to one side, but this becomes difficult to handle as ships get larger. The development of the stern rudder allows larger vessels to be constructed. It consists of a large central paddle mounted on a post at the rear of the ships. It is moved by handle at the top of the post, which may require several men on larger ships. The rudder post is the strongest part of a ship, and traditionally made of elm.}
{Tech Paddle Wheel}
{Paddle Wheel}
{Tech Paddle Wheel Desc}
{River ships are traditionally rowed, but the rowing action is not particularly efficient for large ships where the rower sits high above the water line. Paddle wheels driven by men on treadle paddles are more efficient, and can propel river ships to greater speeds, while removing the vulnerable oars which can easily be damaged by enemy attacks.}
{Tech Star Charts}
{Star Charts}
{Tech Star Charts Desc}
{An accurate map of the stars in the sky is of great use to sailors who are out of sight of land. It allows then to accurately estimate how far north or south they are, and gives them some idea of their rate and direction of travel.}
{Tech Marine Compass}
{Marine Compass}
{Tech Marine Compass Desc}
{Although pieces of lodestone have long been known to orient north / south when suspended in floated in water, the effect is weak and unreliable. The development of a magnetized iron needle, and a mounting suitable for a ship at sea, allow the compass to become a most useful instrument, that allows the mariner to know his direction of facing by either day or night.  }
{Tech Mahjong}
{Mahjon}
{Tech Mahjong Desc}
{TODO}
{Tech Chrome Plating}
{Chrome Plating}
{Tech Chrome Plating Desc}
{TODO}
