{Tumen Horse Archers}
{Tumen Horse Archers}
{Tumen Horse Archers Desc}
{These lightly armored horse archers are the mainstay of the Tumen. With their powerful bows and expert marksmanship, they can subject an enemy to withering fire, before quickly withdrawing if threatened. Their mobility makes them excellent at scouting and outflanking, and their discipline allows them to rapidly concentrate at vulnerable points.}
{Tumen Lancers}
{Tumen Lancers}
{Tumen Lancers Desc}
{These heavy cavalry deliver a heavy charge capable of sweeping away most opponents, be they mounted or on foot. As with all Tumen troops they are organized in troops of ten with each man being responsible for the actions of the others. This fosters courage, brotherhood and discipline making them a tool a general can rely on in the final stages of a battle.}
{Tumen Heavy Cavalry}
{Tumen Heavy Cavalry}
{Tumen Heavy Cavalry Desc}
{With solid armor and powerful bows, this unit has the mobility to match enemy light cavalry, and the equipment to outshoot and outfight them. Against other types of opponent, they can delivery a withering barrage of fire that few can endure for long, and are quite capable of engaging in close combat.}
{Keshik}
{Keshik}
{Keshik Desc}
{These are the Khan's elite guards. They guard him and his family by day and night, and serve as the reserve in battle. They are recruited from the sons of the commanders of thousands and hundreds, and outrank these commanders. While it is a great honor to serve in the Keshik, its members also serve as hostages to ensure the loyalty of unit commanders.}
{Algincin Scouts}
{Algincin Scouts}
{Algincin Scouts Desc}
{A commander cannot be confident of victory in a military campaign without sound intelligence on the enemy. This is gathered by the Algincin who ride two days ahead of the main body to scout out the opponent's strength and dispositions. Composed of brave-hearted, sharp-sighted men on the swiftest horses, they report back the information their  general needs to make a sound plan.}
{Driven Civilians}
{Driven Civilians}
{Driven Civilians Desc}
{These unarmed civilians are rounded up from the countryside or conquered cities, and driven forward in front of the main force by officers with whips. The mass of bodies protect soldiers behind from the missiles of city defenders, and their corpses can help fill ditches and moats. However, they are mainly a tool of psychological warfare putting more pressure on a city's defenders to surrender and avoid further spilling the blood of their own people.}
{Travelling Party}
{Travelling Party}
{Travelling Party Desc}
{This is party of travellers, together with their families, servants and livestock.}
{Temuchins Family}
{Temuchin's Family}
{Temuchins Family Desc}
{This is Temuchin's family. Himself, his mother Hoelun, brothers and sister, half brothers and their mother. Also their servants and any friends who joined them.}
{Horde}
{Nomad Horde}
{Horde Desc}
{The horde is a travelling town, able to move from place to place bringing all its facilities with it. Small carts suffice for the possessions of the common folk, but the great yurts of the lords are moved on giant wagons pulled by many horses or oxen.
Whenever this unit stops at a site suitable to found a settlement, one is automatically created with all the buildings and people it previously had. When this unit moves, the settlement is removed and replaced at the horde's new position. If the unit cannot create a settlement at the end of  the turn, its population and flocks will decline due to lack of food.}
{Iron Pagodas}
{Iron Pagodas}
{Iron Pagodas Desc}
{This elite unit wears the heaviest armor ever fielded in China. They are armored from head to toe, with even their faces protected by a mask or chainmail veil. They are primarily shock cavalry, but are also trained to fight efficiently on foot.}
{Meng'an Cavalry}
{Meng'an Cavalry}
{Meng'an Cavalry Desc}
{These units are the backbone of the Jin Dynasty army. Recruited from ethnic Jurchen tribal groups of the same name, each three-thousand households is responsible for raising and equipping one unit of one thousand men. The unit mixes two ranks of heavily armed cavalry lancers, with three ranks of more lightly armed horse archers. Thus mobility, shock and missile power are combined into one multi-purpose unit. }
{Iron Sparrowhawks}
{Iron Sparrowhawks}
{Iron Sparrowhawks Desc}
{The Iron Sparrowhawks are the elite unit of the Xi Xia army. They are a heavy cavalry unit that combines both shock power and mobility. They move swiftly to where they are needed, and launch a powerful charge. If this is not successful, they prefer to retreat rather than become bogged down.}
{Foot Treaders}
{Foot Sloggers}
{Foot Treaders Desc}
{While the armies of Xi Xia are primarily mounted, there are places where foot soldiers are more suitable. This elite unit of lightly armed infantry specializes in operating in difficult terrain where cavalry cannot operate effectively.}
{Palace Ghulams}
{Palace Ghulams}
{Palace Ghulams Desc}
{These units are the Sultan's elite guard. As with other Ghulam units, they are composed mainly of Turkish slaves, which does not alter their high status. Well armed and armored lancers, they are able to launch devastating charges on both foot and mounted units.}
{Ghulams Archers}
{Ghulam Archers}
{Ghulams Archers Desc}
{These are slave soldiers mainly composed of Turks from the Khurasan region. Despite this, they are highly trained professional soldiers. They fight as heavy cavalry mainly relying on archery, but are also able to fight hand-to-hand with their skull crushing maces. Their armor and close order gives them the edge in archery duels with lighter horse archers.}
{Ghulams Heavy Archers}
{Ghulams Heavy Archers}
{Ghulams Heavy Archers Desc}
{These are slave soldiers mainly composed of Turks from the Khurasan region. Despite this, they are highly trained professional soldiers. They fight as heavy cavalry mainly relying on archery, but are also able to fight hand-to-hand with their skull crushing maces. With their armored horses, they are well protected from enemy return fire.}
{Atabeg Archers}
{Atabegs}
{Atabeg Archers Desc}
{There units consist of Iranian noblemen and their retainers. They fight as armored horse archers, clustering together to fire dense volleys of arrows. They also have the skill and morale to fight at close quarters with their scimitars if need be. They are effective troops, even if sometimes a little touchy.}
{Turkoman Mercenaries}
{Turkoman Mercenaries}
{Turkoman Mercenaries Desc}
{Many small bands of Turkic tribesmen have infiltrated into the spaces between the great cities of Iran. Fighting as fierce light horse archers, they are happy to sell their services to whomever has the means to pay them.}
{Dailami Guard}
{Dailami Guard}
{Dailami Guard Desc}
{Recruited from the mountainous regions of Iran, the Dailami's fairly light  equipment and flexible formation allow them to operate effectively in difficult terrain. However, they also have enough training and protection to fight as heavy infantry in the battle line.}
{IT Army Swordsmen}
{Trained Swordsmen}
{IT Army Swordsmen Desc}
{These units with their razor sharp swords excel at fighting enemy infantry armed with longer more cumbersome weapons, and retain their effectiveness in difficult terrain. Their weakness is their vulnerability to cavalry charges.}
{IT Militia Swordsmen}
{Peasant Militia Swordsmen}
{IT Militia Swordsmen Desc}
{Armed with sharp scimitars, these men excel in close-in fighting. Enemy units with spears and halberds may hold them at bay for a while, but eventually the swordsmen will force their way through the enemy spear wall, and engage in some close range butchery. They are also able to operate effectively in difficult terrain, but are vulnerable to cavalry charges in the open.}
{IT Militia Spear Archers}
{Mixed Spear / Archers}
{IT Militia Spear Archers Desc}
{These solid heavy spearmen are excellent at repelling cavalry attacks. With the rear ranks having bows instead of spears, they can also inflict casualties at range.}
{IT Army Spear Archers}
{Trained Supported Spearmen}
{IT Army Spear Archers Desc}
{These well trained men are comprised mainly of heavy spearmen who will stoutly resist attacks from both cavalry and infantry. However, the rear ranks are equipped with bows to enable them to inflict damage on enemies who do not dare to close with them.}
{Tarim Guard Archers}
{Guard Archers}
{Tarim Guard Archers Desc}
{Recruited mainly from the city folk, these well trained and equipped foot archers are prepared to do whatever it takes to defend their homes.}
{BD Town To Horde}
{Convert To Horde}
{BD Town To Horde Desc}
{Construct wagons to move all the people and buildings. After completion a horde unit will be added to the garrison, and the settlement will move wherever that unit moves.}
{BD Assyrian Church I}
{Nestorian Church}
{BD Assyrian Church I Desc}
{This is a place where Christians can meet and pray together. A local priest provides religious instruction and officiates at ceremonies. In the Nestorian Church, the priest and his followers are often skilled in medicine and surgery, caring for those in need.}
{BD Mosque I}
{Mosque}
{BD Mosque I Desc}
{This a place where followers of the Prophet Muhammad, peace be upon him, gather to pray and listen to religious instruction. It contains separate areas for men and women, and a place to wash before prayer. It also serves as a focus for the community providing education, social welfare and dispute resolution.}
{BD Mosque II}
{Grand Mosque}
{BD Mosque II Desc}
{With domes and towers, this is an  impressive building that shows the glory of Islam. Imams call the faithful to prayer five times a day, from its lofty minarets. The mosque also functions as a center of learning, attracting scholars from far and wide to exchange ideas.}
{BD Mosque III}
{Great Mosque}
{BD Mosque III Desc}
{This is a fabulous richly decorated building, that shows off the wealth and power of the ruler, who has a special area set aside for himself and his family. The interior space is divided by arches and columns, all richly decorated with expensive materials gathered from all corners of the world.}
{BD Carpet Maker}
{Carpet Maker}
{BD Carpet Maker Desc}
{Here workers spin and card fine wool into the thicker warps needed for carpets. Others work at looms, weaving the thicker strands together with thinner ones to produce intricate patterns designed by the resident artists. Other short strands may be wrapped around the warp to produce the pile on the carpet.}
{BD Weaver}
{Weaving Shed}
{BD Weaver Desc}
{Simple cloth can be woven at home, but attractive patterned cloth requires more sophisticated draw-looms. Here, teams of skilled weavers produce quantities of cloth for the local notables, and for trade to other communities.}
{HS Horde Settlement Default Name}
{Horde {0}}
{UI CC Not allowed in horde settlement}
{Not allowed in horde settlements.}
{TI Zhennan Wood}
{Zhennan Wood}
{TI Falcons}
{Falcons}
{TI Bamboo}
{Bamboo}
{TI Sable Fur}
{Sable Fur}
{TI Carpets}
{Fine Carpets}
{TI Textiles}
{Textiles}
{TI Glass}
{Glassware}
{MR Bamboo}
{Bamboo}
{MR Bamboo Desc}
{The tall straight bamboo stems that grow here are  valuable for construction. A settlement that controls (or has adjacent territory) to this resource can trade them for additional income. }
{MR ZhennanWood}
{Zhennan Wood}
{MR ZhennanWood Desc}
{The tall straight evergreen trees here produce wood that is much prized for furniture making and palace construction. The finest logs are so valuable that only royalty can afford them.  A settlement that controls (or has adjacent territory) to this resource can trade them for additional income. }
{MR Sable}
{Sable}
{MR Sable Desc}
{The small carnivorous animals who live here, have fur which is greatly prized for its warmth and smoothness, A settlement that controls (or has adjacent territory) to this resource can trade the fur for additional income. }
{MR Falcons}
{Falcons}
{MR Falcons Desc}
{Hunting with birds is a favorite pastime of the aristocracy, and they will pay handsomely for fine falcons. A settlement that controls (or has adjacent territory) to this resource can trade them for additional income. }
{MR Goats}
{Goats}
{MR Goats Desc}
{A few wild goats scratch a living on the hillside, but are still a valuable source of nourishment. This will increase by {0} the food production of any settlement that controls it, or has adjacent territory.}
{MR Silk Road West}
{Silk Road West}
{MR Silk Road West Desc}
{Merchants travelling to and from the East pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Silk Road East}
{Silk Road East}
{MR Silk Road East Desc}
{Merchants travelling to and from the West pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Silk Road Central}
{Silk Road Central}
{MR Silk Road Central Desc}
{Merchants travelling between the East and  the West pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Spice Road}
{Spice Road}
{MR Spice Road Desc}
{Merchants travelling from and to India pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Sable Road}
{Sable Road}
{MR Sable Road Desc}
{Merchants bringing furs from the North pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Falcon Road}
{Falcon Road}
{MR Falcon Road Desc}
{Merchants bringing hunting falcons from the wilderness pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Trade Route2}
{Trade Route}
{MR Trade Route2 Desc}
{Merchant caravans pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0}.}
{MR Sea Trade Route2}
{Sea Trade Route}
{MR Sea Trade Route2 Desc}
{Merchant ships pass through here. A settlement controlling this resource can tax them for {0} if you have the technology {1}.}
{Unit Set Islamic Turk}
{Islamic Turk}
{Unit Set Jurchen Jin}
{Jurchen Jin}
{Unit Set Xi Xia}
{Xi Xia}
{Unit Set TarimB}
{Tarim Basin Buddhist}
{UI SE Personal Names Islamic}
{Islamic}
{UI SE Place Names Central Asian}
{Central Asian}
{UI SE Place Names Tarim Basin}
{Tarim Basin}
{UI SE Place Names Turk}
{Turk}
{UI SE Place Names Special Use}
{Special Use}
{UI SE Personal Names Turk}
{Turk}
{TT Unnamed Horde}
{Unnamed Horde}
{TT Moving Horde Stats}
{Population: {0} -- Flocks: {1}}
{TT Horde Buildings under Construction}
{Buildings Under Construction: {0}}
{TT Convert Horde To Town}
{Convert to a Fixed Town}
{TT Trade Network Monopoly}
{If you control all {0} resources with this symbol, then the tax income from them is doubled.}
{TT Trade Network Supply}
{The merchants supply the following items:}
{TT Trade Network Demand}
{If the controlling settlement has the building {0} it can trade the  merchants the following items:}
{TT Settlement Surrender Text}
{There is a {0}% chance that this settlement will peacefully surrender if attacked. The following factors affect this chance:}
{TT Terror Factors 1}
{A nearby settlement was recently destroyed by the attacker.}
{TT Teror Factors 2}
{Terrifying incendiary weapons have been used against it.}
{TT Teror Factors 3}
{It has been attacked by Driven Civilians}
{TT Terror Factors 4}
{The settlement is completely surrounded and out of food.}
{TT Terror Factors 5}
{{0} is inspiring the garrison to hold out.}
{UI Confirm Convert Settlement Title}
{Convert to a Fixed Town}
{UI Confirm Convert Settlement Msg}
{Disband the horde unit and convert the settlement to a fixed town. This will allow land improvements and more buildings, but you will no longer be able to move it.}
{UI No Improvements For Horde}
{Horde settlements may not make any land improvements or construct external buildings. To allow improvements convert the settlement to a fixed town using the button at the bottom of the screen.}
{UI CC No Room For Horde Unit}
{Garrison is full. Needs space for one unit.}
{UI CC No Flocks}
{Only settlements with flocks can become hordes.}
{UI CC Farms}
{Settlements with farms cannot become hordes.}
{UI CC Non Horde Buildings}
{The settlement already contains buildings that are not allowed in hordes.}
{UI CC Not Town}
{Only town level settlements can convert.}
{UI Player Mission Reminder Title}
{Mission}
{UI Settlement Surrenders}
{Settlement Surrenders}
{UI Settlement Falls}
{Settlement Has Fallen}
{UI VC Unavailable}
{This victory condition is unavailable.}
{UI Cannot Attack}
{You cannot attack this faction until it is unlocked by events in the scenario.}
{UI Cannot Issue Edicts}
{You are not yet important enough to issue edicts.}
{UI Cannot Research}
{You are not yet important enough to research technology.}
{UI Cannot Do Diplomacy}
{You are not yet important enough to conduct diplomacy.}
{UI Cannot contact until unlocked.}
{You cannot contact this faction until they are unlocked by events in the scenario.}
{UI Technology Acquired}
{Technology Acquired}
{UI Building cannot be destroyed}
{This building cannot be destroyed.}
{UI Destruction unrest message}
{Destroying this building will cause {0} unrest for {1} turns.}
{UI Building destroyed effect}
{{0} Destroyed}
{UI Mission Failed Text}
{Mission Failed}
{UI Mission Failed Text 1}
{You have failed to complete your mission. Your authority is reduced by {0}}
{UI Mission Failed Text 2}
{You have failed to complete your mission. Your allies have cancelled your alliance in disappointment.}
{UI Faction Tag Muslim}
{Muslim}
{UI Faction Tag Christian}
{Christian}
{UI Faction Tag Buddhist}
{Buddhist}
{UI SE Portrait Type}
{Portrait Type}
{UI SE Portrait Type Chinese}
{Chinese}
{UI SE Portrait Type Mongol}
{Mongol}
{UI SE Button Claim Lands}
{Claim Land for Flocks}
{UI SE Allowed Victory Conditions}
{Victory Conditions}
{UI SE Faction Type Frozen}
{Frozen}
{FE Game Time of the Mongols}
{Time of the Mongols}
{Time Of The Mongols Desc}
{This campaign covers the lands that would be conquered by Genghis Khan as they were at the start of the Thirteenth Century. You may play any faction and win by the standard victory conditions.}
{FE Game Life of Genghis Khan}
{Life of Genghis Khan}
{Life of Genghis Khan Desc}
{In this campaign you take the role of Temuchin, who would later take the title of Genghis Khan. It presents the key moments in his life as a series missions that you must complete to progress. You win if you can match his conquests within the allowed number of turns.}
{Help}
{### Trans ### }
{HPTitle Horde Settlements}
{Horde Settlements}
{HPHeading Horde Settlements 1}
{Introduction}
{HPText Horde Settlements 1}
{Horde settlements are a special type of settlement that can be moved around the map. Each horde settlement has an accompanying horde unit. If this unit is moved, the entire settlement is packed up and loaded onto the unit. If the unit finishes its movement on a hex where a settlement could normally be created, then the settlement is recreated on that spot.}
{HPText Horde Settlements 2}
{This mobility can be used defensively to move vulnerable settlements away from threatening enemies, or offensively by providing a travelling support base where you can replenish depleted units, and recruit new ones.}
{HPHeading Horde Settlements Creation}
{Creating a Horde Settlement}
{HPText Horde Settlements Creation 1}
{Horde settlements can only be created by herder factions that have the "Iron-Wheeled Carts" technology. They can be created in one of two ways. Firstly by recruiting a horde unit in an existing settlement, which effectively creates a new settlement that will be deployed  when the horde unit moves away to a suitable location.}
{HPText Horde Settlements Creation 2}
{The second way is to convert an existing settlement to a horde by building the "Town to Horde" settlement upgrade on the building screen. When completed, this will create a horde unit in the garrison, and the existing settlement with all its buildings and people will be attached to it. }
{HPText Horde Settlements Creation 3}
{A horde settlement can be turned back into a normal one using the button on the bottom right of the settlement screen. Convert it to a normal settlement first if you wish to disband it.}
{HPHeading Horde Settlements Restrictions}
{Restrictions}
{HPText Horde Settlements Restrictions}
{Horde settlements are not allowed to have any farms or external buildings, and some internal buildings are also prohibited. They can only be created from towns that do not yet have sufficient population to be upgraded to a city.}
{HPHeading Horde Settlement Attrition}
{Attrition}
{HPText Horde Settlement Attrition}
{A horde unit can only deploy its settlement in a location where a normal settlement could be founded. Therefore it can't deploy within the territory of, or too close to another settlement, adjacent to water etc. If a horde unit is unable to deploy its settlement, then it cannot produce any food, apart from two for domestic production. The population will eat any stored food, and then any flock animals they have. When these are exhausted they will suffer attrition due to starvation. Flock animals will also suffer attrition due to lack of grazing. However, the horde can make use of any food resource in or adjacent to their hex unless another settlement is already using it.}
{HPLink Horde Settlements}
{Horde Settlements}
{HPTitle Settlement Surrender}
{Peaceful Surrender}
{HPHeading Settlement Surrender }
{Peaceful Surrender}
{HPHeading Settlement Surrender Text 1}
{Sometimes a settlement will surrender peacefully at the start of a battle, or when an enemy unit reaches a breach.}
{HPHeading Settlement Surrender Text 2}
{This is most likely to occur when a barbarian faction employs terror tactics to intimidate the city. These include destroying nearby settlements, assaulting the settlement with driven civilians, or using terrifying incendiary weapons in the assault. A city may also surrender if totally surrounded and out of food. The number of skulls on top of the city tab give an indication of how likely the city is to surrender.}
{HPHeading Settlement Surrender Text 3}
{If a character is in the city, the chances of it surrendering will be decreased according to his Ren value.}
{HPLink Settlement Surrender}
{Peaceful Surrender}
{Advice}
{### Trans ### }
{Advice Title Spread Terror}
{Spread Terror}
{Advice Text Spread Terror}
{Destroying this settlement will speed terror and make nearby ones more likely to surrender.}
{Advice Title Horde Attrition}
{Horde Attrition}
{Advice Text Horde Attrition}
{Your horde unit cannot deploy its settlement here, and may suffer losses to its people and flocks. Try to move to one of the indicated hexes where a settlement may be deployed.}
{Advice Title Horde Support}
{Horde Support}
{Advice Text Horde Support}
{A horde settlement can advance with your armies and provide a convenient place to replenish depleted units. If deployed it replenishes units in the same way as a normal settlement.}
{Advice Title Convert To Horde}
{Convert to Horde}
{Advice Text Convert To Horde}
{You can convert this settlement to a horde and move it to a more favourable, or less threatened location.}
{ED Kurultai}
{Call a Kurultai}
{ED Kurultai Desc}
{Summon the clan chiefs to gather and pay homage to their leader, and to bestow the title "Khan" upon him. Let there be feasting and entertainments, and tell them that the Khan will reward his loyal vassals. 
If any do not assent to our leader taking this title, let them stay away.}
{ED Great Kurultai}
{Call a Great Kurultai}
{ED Great Kurultai Desc}
{Now that I have subdued all the people of the felt walled tents, and united them into one nation. It is fitting that I, as leader of this new nation take the title "Genghis Khan" as a signal to all of my power and majesty. Let the leaders of the people gather together at a great festival to pledge loyalty to me, and to hear the new laws I shall give them.}
{ED Yam Messenger System}
{Yam Messenger System}
{ED Yam Messenger System Desc}
{Our empire is vast and communication within it is slow. Let us establish a system of posts a day's journey apart supplied  with provisions, accommodation and fresh horses. Messengers on important business can exchange their tired horses for fresh ones at these stations, and thus be able to cover 200 miles in one day. Nearby towns shall support these stations as their tribute to the Khan.}
{ED Establish Keshik}
{Establish Keshik}
{ED Establish Keshik Desc}
{The army is composed of many tribes, and loyalty to the tribe may be greater than loyalty to the Khan. To combat this, let an elite guard be established composed on the sons or younger brothers of the leaders of the thousands and hundreds in the army. The Keshik will serve as the Khan's personal bodyguard, an elite reserve in battle, and a training ground for future officers. It will also instill loyalty to the Khan in its members.}
{ED Forbid Looting}
{Forbid Looting}
{ED Forbid Looting Desc}
{It is the natural right of the victors to take the possessions and women of the defeated, but looting during a battle takes soldiers away from the fight and allows defeated enemies to escape. Therefore looting during battle is strictly forbidden on pain of death. All loot shall be gathered after the battle, and divided fairly among the soldiers present.}
{ED Freedom of Worship}
{Freedom of Worship}
{ED Freedom of Worship Desc}
{There is only one God in Heaven, but men reach him in different ways, and each man should be free to worship God in the way that he sees fit. Furthermore, let all religious leaders of whatever faith be exempt from taxation and public service.}
{ED Tax Exemption}
{Tax Exemption}
{ED Tax Exemption Desc}
{For the improvement of the realm we should encourage men of learning and skill to ply their trades. Accordingly, doctors, artisans, undertakers, merchants and religious leaders shall be exempt from personal taxation and labour service.}
{ED Yassa Law}
{Yassa Law}
{ED Yassa Law Desc}
{In the past the steppe has been a lawless place full of violence and suffering. To end this, the law will be imposed upon all, and a chief judge appointed to  record and administer the law.
Stealing of women and livestock is forbidden. Anyone guilty of theft must pay back nine times the value of the stolen items. Anyone guilty of hurting a horse's eyes shall be executed, as should anyone guilty of homosexual practices. Anyone eating in front of another without offering them food shall also be put to death.}
{EFF CancelSuccessionPenalty}
{Cancels authority penalty for succession.}
{EFF CancelDistancePenalty}
{Cancels the distance to capital unrest effect.}
{EFF EnablesUnits}
{Enables recruitment of units}
{EFF IncreaseBooty}
{Increases the booty taken by sacking a settlement:}
{Tech Iron Wheeled Carts}
{Iron-Wheeled Carts}
{Tech Iron Wheeled Carts Desc}
{If a nomadic lifestyle is to be anything but basic subsistence, then a means of moving large and heavy tools and possessions is needed. These tough carts have wooden wheels taller than a man, with the rim covered in iron. Pulled by horses or oxen, they allow movement of large tents, food supplies, and the blacksmith's forge.}
{Tech Terror Tactics}
{Terror Tactics}
{Tech Terror Tactics Desc}
{Sieging a well defended city can be a long and costly affair. Much loss can be avoided if the city can be terrified into surrendering without a fight. Tactics to achieve this include using local civilians as human shields in an assault, firing incendiary projectiles or diseased corpses into the city, or promising that any city that resists will be destroyed, and any that surrender will be spared.}
{Tech Nerge}
{Nerge}
{Tech Nerge Desc}
{The Nerge is a large scale winter hunt that also serves  as a military training exercise. The army surrounds a large area of terrain, and over a period of weeks slowly contracts the area in a tighter circle, thus entraping all the local wild animals. Anyone allowing an animal to escape is punished. When the circle has contracted to three miles across, the Khan and his entourage hunt the densely-packed game.}
{Tech Tengrism}
{Tengrism}
{Tech Tengrism Desc}
{Tengri is the Blue Sky and Eternal Heaven, the creator of everything. Between the blue sky and brown earth, human beings exist, Tengri tries to guide them by sending his sacred animals among them. Although every man's soul is connected to Tengri, it takes a Shaman to read Heaven's will, or ask for its favour.}
{Tech Loyal Followers}
{Loyal Followers}
{Tech Loyal Followers Desc}
{Traditionally, a leader relies on his extended family as trustworthy advisors and lieutenants, however a khan is not always blessed with smart or reliable relatives. Having been abandoned by his clan when his father died, Temuchin must learn to rely on the friends who have proved loyal and capable over the years, and promote those over lesser men related by blood.}
{Tech Allegiance}
{Allegiance}
{Tech Allegiance Desc}
{It is of the utmost importance that a follower is loyal to his Khan, and that his Khan can rely on him. A free man may voluntarily change his Khan, but there is no worse crime than to betray him to his enemy.}
{Tech Protection of Heaven}
{Protection of Heaven}
{Tech Protection of Heaven Desc}
{Temuchin was born with fire in his eyes and light on his face, his fate ordained by Heaven. When in danger, he will be protected by the holy mountain, and the will of Tengri.}
{Tech Mongol Destiny}
{Mongol Destiny}
{Tech Mongol Destiny Desc}
{As there is one ruler in Heaven, there should be one ruler on Earth. It is the will of Heaven that Temuchin and the Mongol people bring about this situation, and unite all the peoples of the world under one Khan.}
{Tech Decimal Army Organization}
{Decimal Army Organization}
{Tech Decimal Army Organization Desc}
{Armies can operate more efficiently if they are well organized. In a decimal system, each man is allocated to an Arban of ten men. A man can never change his Arban, and if any one of them commits an infraction all are punished. Ten Arban are organized into a Zuun, and ten Zuun  are organized into a Mingghan. Ten Mingghan  are organized into a Tumen of ten thousand men. This system allows an army to efficiently controlled, supplied and trained.}
{Tech Steppe Medicine}
{Steppe Medicine}
{Tech Steppe Medicine Desc}
{The needs and resources of the pastoral nomad are different from those of sedentary peoples. Their lifestyle of riding and animal breaking can result in many broken bones, and constant warfare involves mainly arrow wounds. Important techniques include manipulation to fix broken bones and dislocations, sucking out poison or infection from a wound, and placing the patient's body inside a fresh animal carcass to help seal wounds and maintain blood flow.}
{Tech Khanate Administration}
{Khanate Administration}
{Tech Khanate Administration Desc}
{A petty Khan may rule by merely voicing his wishes and relying on a few trusted cohorts to enforce them. However, a mighty empire needs fixed rules to ensure obedience, generals to gather the army, and an administration of trusted men to gather taxes and tribute.}
{Tech Qada Anda Nokor}
{Qada Anda Nokor}
{Tech Qada Anda Nokor Desc}
{The ties of marriage, sworn brotherhood and friendship respectively that bind people together in a tribal society. Used skillfully, a lord can built a network of loyal and trusted supporters that can provide information, advice and physical assistance.}
{Tech Reconnaissance}
{Reconnaissance}
{Tech Reconnaissance Desc}
{Victory can only be certain if a general has full knowledge of the enemy. Before starting a campaign he should seek knowledge from spies, or by questioning merchants. Once it has begun, he should send scouts out riding two days in advance of the army to report on the enemy's positions.}
{Tech Use All Talents}
{Use All Talents}
{Tech Use All Talents Desc}
{The Mongols live a simple life, excelling in the skills needed to survive in the grasslands, forests and mountains. Men of other nations have other skills, have invented many wonderful things, and mastered many arts. Scholars and artisans should be spared from slaughter and put to work for the good of the empire.}
{Tech Throat Singing}
{Throat Singing}
{Tech Throat Singing Desc}
{A skilled singer can manipulate their mouth, lips and larynx to simultaneously produce a base note, and one or more overtone notes. Originating as a way to mimic the sounds of nature, it can also be combined with conventional instruments to produce powerful musical performances.}
{Tech Story Telling}
{Story Telling}
{Tech Story Telling Desc}
{In pre-literate world, information is preserved by story tellers who recount the histories of past peoples and times. Using tricks of meter and stock phrases, epic tales can be preserved down the generations. Performers combine the core of the tale with improvised elements to keep the entertainment compelling.}
{Tech Islam}
{Islam}
{Tech Islam Desc}
{Follows of Islam believe that there is only one god, Allah, who is the creator and sustainer of the world. Human beings must surrender to his will, which he revealed to the prophet Muhammad, and which is written down in the holy book, the Koran. Its followers form a worldwide community that transcends race and language, but must follow a strict religious regime that includes praying towards Mecca five times a day.}
{Tech Carpet Weaving}
{Carpet Weaving}
{Tech Carpet Weaving Desc}
{A woolen carpet may be utilitarian floor covering, but it can also be a work of art suitable for the homes of kings and princes, or to be given as a diplomatic gift. Such carpets are made with fine wool or silk with complex scenes or geometric patterns woven into them. Precious stones may embedded to further enhance their beauty.}
{Tech Draw Loom}
{Draw Loom}
{Tech Draw Loom Desc}
{A draw loom is a second frame that sits on top of a basic hand loom, providing a set of pattern shafts that are operated by an assistant. With this device, complex patterns can be woven into cloth of hemp, ramie, wool or silk, to create beautiful bolts of cloth that are much sought after.}
{Tech Wrestling}
{Wrestling}
{Tech Wrestling Desc}
{Wrestling is a manly sport that promotes strength and stamina. Two contestants grip each other and try to force their opponent to touch the ground with some part of their body other than their foot.  Wrestling matches are a popular form of entertainment, and champions are held in high regard.}
{Tech Kurultai}
{Lateral Succession}
{Tech Kurultai Desc}
{In many societies a ruler is automatically succeeded by his first born son. This system has the advantage of clarity, but can lead to children or unfit leaders being placed on the throne. In a lateral system, the nobles of a tribe choose a new king from the old king's brothers and sons. This means that the nation always has a capable and experienced ruler.}
{Tech Sulde}
{Sulde}
{Tech Sulde Desc}
{A sulde is a warriors spirit standard that stands outside his tent. Make from hairs from a stallion attached to a spear, it channels energy from the wind and sun to the warrior. People believe that his spirit becomes entwined with it, and that his soul lives on in it after he dies. The sulde of a great chief will be kept by his people for a long time.}
{Tech Naadam Festival}
{Naadam Festival}
{Tech Naadam Festival Desc}
{The Naadam is a festival where nomadic people gather to celebrate a special occasion. Besides feasting and socializing, there will be singing and dancing performances. Contests are held in the three major sports of wrestling, archery and horse racing.}
{Tech Nestorian Christianity}
{Nestorian Christianity}
{Tech Nestorian Christianity Desc}
{The Nestorians are a branch of Christianity that flourishes in Asia, although their views are regarded as heretical in the Christian lands in the West. Their presence is mainly low key and community-based with an emphasis on providing medical care to the needy.}
{Khwarezm Short}
{Khwarazem}
{Khwarezm Full}
{Khwarazem}
{Khwarezm Desc}
{Khwarazem is the marshy region south of the Aral sea, where the desert is watered by the Amu Darya river. Until recently the rulers  were vassals of the Qara Khitans, but have revolted and quickly taken  control of a large area. Although a devout Muslim, their ruler is in dispute with the Caliph in Bagdad, and also with his mother, a princess of the Kangli Turks. These internal divisions, and the resentment of the newly  conquered territories, mean that this ostensibly powerful empire is in fact rather fragile.}
{Qara Khitans Short}
{Kara Khitans}
{Qara Khitans Full}
{Kara Khitans}
{Qara Khitans Desc}
{When the Khitan Empire was overthrown by the Jurchen, a group led by Yelu Dashi from the western outposts migrated further West rather than submit. Gathering warriors to the cause as they travelled, they established a kingdom in the  region north of the Tian Shan mountains, and soon subjugated the surrounding kingdoms to establish a huge area of dominance from the edges of Iran to the borders of China. Many powerful kingdoms submitted to them, but now some of these are in revolt. Although their subjects are mainly Muslim, The Qara Khitans themselves retain their Buddhist religion, and maintain the trappings of a Chinese state. Their name gave rise to the term Cathay, an early name for China.}
{Qocho Uyghurs Short}
{Qocha}
{Qocho Uyghurs Full}
{Qocha Uyghurs}
{Qocho Uyghurs Desc}
{The Uyghurs were originally a Turkic people who controlled a vast empire across the Asian steppe. Eventually they were overthrown and a remnant of them fled to Qocho, an important city on the Silk Road, and established a kingdom there. Despite their nomadic origins, they now become a settled people living from agriculture and trade. Current day Uyghurs are Muslims, but at this point in history they were Buddhists.}
{Qangli Turks Short}
{Kangli}
{Qangli Turks Full}
{Kangli Turks}
{Qangli Turks Desc}
{The Kangli are a loose confederation of Turkic tribes who have lived in the area of Kazakhstan and Western Siberia for hundreds of years. They are primarily nomadic herders, but also control some cities around the Aral and Caspian Seas. They are a source of mercenary soldiers for much of the Islamic world.}
{The Naiman Short}
{Naiman}
{The Naiman Full}
{The Naiman}
{The Naiman Desc}
{The Naiman are a Turkic people dominating the Altai mountain region. Their flocks thrive in the high meadows, though they also practice settled agriculture. They are unusual among the peoples of the region in having adopted Christianity as their religion, and follow the teachings of the Assyrian Church. Some believe they are the source of the legend of Prester John, the powerful Asian king who it was hoped would one day assist the Crusaders}
{Xi Xia Short}
{Xi Xia}
{Xi Xia Full}
{Xi Xia}
{Xi Xia Desc}
{The Xi Xia, also known as Tanguts are a people originally from Tibet, who took advantage of the chaos following the collapse of the Tang Dynasty to establish a state astride the Silk Road as it runs through the Gansu Corridor. The state combines both the Chinese cities along this route, and nomadic peoples living in the Ordos loop. The state is rich from trade, civilized and fiercely Buddhist. They maintain a powerful military force that has enabled them to resist attacks from the more populous areas of China to the East.}
{Jurchen Jin Short}
{Jin}
{Jurchen Jin Full}
{Jin Dynasty}
{Jurchen Jin Desc}
{The Jin (Golden) Dynasty was founded by the Jurchen people from the forests of Manchuria, and rules most of Northern China. While the ethnic Jurchen remain an elite, their empire is very much a Chinese one, and not substantially different from the administrations of other dynasties.}
{Khitans Short}
{Khitans}
{Khitans Full}
{The Khitans}
{Khitans Desc}
{The Khitans are a Mongolian people living on the western edge of Manchuria. They practice a mixture of farming and herding. They once had a significant empire dominating the Mongolian steppe and parts of Northern China, but they were overthrown by the Jurchen people from further east, and are now vassals of the Jin dynasty those founded.}
{Tatars Short}
{Tatars}
{Tatars Full}
{The Tatars}
{Tatars Desc}
{The Tatars are a nomadic herding people living in the eastern part of Mongolia. They are fierce horsemen similar to the other peoples of the area, but also the richest people on the Steppe due to their proximity to, and trade with China. Later the term Tatar became synonymous with Mongol, but at this point in history they are still a distinct, though related tribe.}
{Song Genghis Short}
{Song}
{Song Genghis Full}
{Song Dynasty}
{Song Genghis Desc}
{The empire ruled by the Song Dynasty is the most advanced in the world, reaching economic and cultural heights that will not be matched elsewhere for hundreds of years. Their wealth come from large scale manufacture of iron, steal, textiles and porcelain, facilitated by banks, paper money and joint stock companies. However their cultural and business pursuits mean they have little interest in war and often struggle to repel the attackers of less civilized, but fiercer, peoples. Most of their empire is in Southern China, and only a few northern cities are featured on this map.}
{Kereits Short}
{Kereits}
{Kereits Full}
{Kereit Khanate}
{Kereits Desc}
{The Kereits are the most powerful people on the Mongolian Steppe. Similar to other peoples of the area, they are primarily nomadic herders, but they also have a fixed capital city supported by farming and trade.}
{Merkits Short}
{Merkits}
{Merkits Full}
{The Merkits}
{Merkits Desc}
{The Merkits are a confederation of tribes living on the northernmost part of Mongolia. They practice both farming and pastoralism, but their bleak cold lands produce little wealth. They are renowned archers, and also famous for their magic.}
{Khamag Mongols Short}
{Mongols}
{Khamag Mongols Full}
{The Mongols}
{Khamag Mongols Desc}
{The Mongols are a tough herding people living on the northern edge of the Mongolian Steppe. They are poor and uncivilized, but are great horsemen and fierce fighters. Traditionally they  devote much of their energy to fighting each other. However, a new young leader has brought temporary unity and a chance for them to be a force in the world.}
{Karakhanids Short}
{Karakhanids}
{Karakhanids Full}
{Karakhanid Khanate}
{Karakhanids Desc}
{The Karakhanid Khanate is the remaining eastern part of a previously much larger empire that ruled much of Central Asia. The original founders were nomadic Turkic tribes who converted to Islam, but many of them adopted the culture and lifestyle of the mainly Iranian subjects they rule over. Although they are much diminished, they are still wealthy from controlling an important part of the Silk Road and have access to the famous horses of the Ferghana valley. Previously they were vassals of the Kara Khitans, but are now in revolt.}
{The Kirghiz Short}
{The Kirghiz}
{The Kirghiz Full}
{The Kirghiz}
{The Kirghiz Desc}
{The Kirghiz are a people of mixed Caucasian and Asian stock, possibly related to the Dingling. Once they dominated much of Central Asia, with many migrating to the area of modern day Kirghizstan, but others still live in the their original area in the Altai Mountains, an area famous for fine furs and large horses. Many of their people are nomadic herders, but some live in settled farming communities. Their royal family claim descent from Li Ling, a brave but foolish Chinese general who defected to the Xiongnu rather than return home in disgrace.}
{Jadaran Mongols Short}
{Jadaran}
{Jadaran Mongols Full}
{Jadaran Mongols}
{Jadaran Mongols Desc}
{A clan of the Mongols from the East.}
{Tayichiud Mongols Short}
{Tayichiud}
{Tayichiud Mongols Full}
{Tayichiud Mongols}
{Tayichiud Mongols Desc}
{A clan of the Mongols. Relatives of Temuchin.}
{Olkhonut Mongols Short}
{Olkhonud}
{Olkhonud Mongols Full}
{Olkhonud Mongols}
{Olkhonud Mongols Desc}
{A clan of the Mongols renowned for their beautiful women. The tribe of Temuchin's wife Borte.}
{UI SE Delete Faction Title}
{Delete Faction ?}
{UI SE Delete Faction Msg}
{Are you sure you want to delete this faction and all its cities and units.}
{CAP Scouting Range}
{Scouting Range}
{CAP Scouting Range Desc}
{Discovers enemy and terrain to a range of {0} hexes}
{CAP Surrender Check}
{Surrender Check}
{CAP Surrender Check Desc1}
{If this unit reaches a breach in a wall (not gate), there is a chance the settlement will surrender.}
{CAP Surrender Check Desc2}
{If this unit reaches a breached wall or destroyed gate, there is a chance the settlement will surrender.}
{CAP Travelling Horde}
{Travelling Horde}
{CAP Travelling Horde Desc}
{The unit is a travelling settlement. Whenever it stops in a suitable location the settlement will be recreated with its population and buildings. If it is unable to recreate the settlement, its population and flocks will decrease.}
{CAP Terror Tactics}
{Terror Tactics}
{CAP Terror Tactics Desc}
{Destroying an enemy settlement will terrify nearby settlements of a similar or smaller size, and there is a chance that they will immediately surrender when attacked.}
{CAP Capture Tech}
{Capture Technology}
{CAP Capture Tech Desc}
{When an enemy settlement is taken, there is a {0}% chance that a technology will be acquired from them.}
{CAP Terrifying Weapon}
{Terrifying Weapon}
{CAP Terrifying Weapon Desc}
{This weapon reduces the morale of nearby enemies by {0}.}
{CAP Terrifying Projectiles}
{Terrifying Projectiles}
{CAP Terrifying Projectiles Desc}
{Reduces the morale of enemy units struck by them by {0} and may also increase the chance of a settlement surrendering.}
{CAP Leader Invulnerable}
{Invulnerable Leader}
{CAP Leader Invulnerable Desc}
{Your faction leader has special protection. He can only be killed if his entire unit is destroyed, and cannot be killed by random disasters.}
{CAP Disaster Medical Care}
{Disaster Medical Care}
{CAP Disaster Medical Care Desc}
{Casualties from disasters and plague reduced by {0}%}
{CAP Produce Zhennan Wood}
{Produces Zhennan Wood}
{CAP Produce Zhennan Wood Desc}
{Produces zhennan wood for trade.}
{CAP Produce Bamboo}
{Produces Bamboo}
{CAP Produce Bamboo Desc}
{Produces bamboo for trade.}
{CAP Produce Falcons}
{Produces Falcons}
{CAP Produce Falcons Desc}
{Produces falcons for trade}
{CAP Produce Sable Fur}
{Produces Sable Fur}
{CAP Produce Sable Fur Desc}
{Produces sable fur for trade.}
{CAP Produce Carpets}
{Produces Carpets}
{CAP Produce Carpets Desc}
{Produces fine carpets for trade.}
{CAP Produce Textiles}
{Produce Textiles}
{CAP Produce Textiles Desc}
{Produces textiles for trade.}
{CAP Produce Glass}
{Produces Glassware}
{CAP Produce Glass Desc}
{Produces glassware for trade.}
{LGK Intro1 Title}
{In The Beginning}
{LGK Intro1 Text}
{In the beginning there was a  grey wolf with his fate ordained by Heaven, and his mate, a beautiful deer. Together  they crossed over a great lake and settled at the source of the Onon River.

And after many generations, their descendant was a man named Yesugei.

  - from the Secret History of the Mongols}
{LGK Intro2 Title}
{Hoelun}
{LGK Intro2 Text}
{One day Yesugei and his brothers were out hunting when they came across a man of the Merkit tribe. The man, Yeke Ciledu, was escorting his new bride Hoelun back to his home. Yesugei and his brothers drove Yeke off and Yesugei took Hoelun to be his own second wife.}
{LGK Intro3 Title}
{Temuchin}
{LGK Intro3 Text}
{And a baby boy was born to Hoelun and Yesugei. The boy had fire in his eyes and light on his face, and in his right hand he grasped a large blood clot which some said was an omen of things to come.

And Yesugei named the boy Temuchin after a captive he had taken in a recent war.. }
{LGK Intro4 Title}
{Introduction}
{LGK Intro4 Text}
{You are nine years old. You are the son of a minor chief, who unfortunately has just died. No-one among your clansmen is willing to take care of your family, so you have been abandoned in the wilderness without  horses.  Apart from your shadows, you have no friends, and are expected to die.

However, your mother is a resourceful strong-willed woman who will not give up easily. She instructs your family group on how to survive by hunting marmots and catching fish, but it is a tough time for you and your brothers.

To survive you must find more substantial food. Move your family group to a hex containing wild game.}
{LGK Mission 1 Title}
{Abandoned}
{LGK Mission 1 Text}
{You are nine years old. You are the son of a minor chief, who unfortunately has just died. No-one among your clansmen is willing to take care of your family, so you have been abandoned in the wilderness without  horses.  Apart from your shadows, you have no friends, and are expected to die.

However, your mother is a resourceful strong willed woman who will not give up easily. She instructs your family group on how to survive by hunting marmots and catching fish, but it is a tough time for you and your brothers.

To survive you must find more substantial food. Move your family group to a hex containing wild game.}
{LGK Mission 2 Title}
{Find Friends}
{LGK Mission 2 Text}
{Thanks to your mother's indomitable spirit your family has managed to survive so far, but hunting is difficult with only crude weapons and no horses.

Although abandoned by your kinsmen, your father had many friends on the steppe, and if you can find them maybe they will give you help.

Move East towards a common camping spot, and hope that friends arrive soon.}
{LGK Event 1 Title}
{Jamuka}
{LGK Event 1 Text}
{You have met a friendly group of travelers from the Jadaran clan who let you stay with them for a while. Amongst them is a boy around your own age called Jamuka. You become close friends, and perform the rite of blood-brotherhood (Anda).

Jamuka is of noble descent, and will prove a valuable ally in future.}
{LGK Event West Title}
{Return West}
{LGK Event West Text}
{All good times must come to end, and now it is time to leave Jamuka's people and return to your home area near the holy mountain "Burkan Kaldun"}
{LGK Event Kill Brother Title}
{Fratricide}
{LGK Event Kill Brother Text}
{You are now fourteen years old, and tension has been building between yourself and your elder half brother Bekter. As he grows into manhood he will become the groups leader, and according to tradition, take your deceased fathers wife, your mother, as his own.

You and your full brother Khasar creep up on him while he is alone, and shoot him dead with an arrow.}
{LGK Event Arrows Title}
{A Bundle of Arrows}
{LGK Event Arrows Text}
{Your mother is furious at your actions, and berates you at length, reminding you how few friends you have. She then asks you to break an arrow in half, which you do easily. She then asks to break a bundle of arrows, and when you are unable to do so, explains that to be alone is to be weak, but to be united is to be strong.

Continue moving west.}
{LGK Mission Borte Title}
{Find Your Wife}
{LGK Mission Borte Text}
{You are now sixteen years old. As a grown man, your unit has now been separated from your family.

Before your father was killed he had taken you to the Olkhonud tribe to choose a future wife. You chose a girl named Borte who was a year  older than you.

Now it is time to claim your bride. Move Temuchin to Borte's family in the indicated hex. Continue moving your family towards Burkan Kaldun.}
{LGK Mission Sable Coat Title}
{Sable Coat}
{LGK Mission Sable Coat Text}
{Congratulations, you have married Borte. She is your trusted companion and love of your life. As her dowry, her father gives you a valuable sable fur coat. Your mother advises you to take it to Togril who is currently the most powerful man on the steppe, and your father's blood brother. His blessing and protection will be invaluable.}
{LGK Event Togril Title}
{Togril's Blessing}
{LGK Event Togril Text}
{Togril is delighted with the coat you present to him. He recalls his debt to your father who helped him reclaim his throne when he had been ousted by his brother. He adopts you as his son.

Togril is the leader of the Kerait Tribe. They are now your allies.
}
{LGK Base Camp Title}
{Base Camp}
{LGK Base Camp Text}
{Now you are married and have the backing of Togril Khan, people of your tribe start to see you as a rising young warrior of noble blood, and some start to look to you for leadership. You establish a base camp at Burkan Kaldun.

You can now start to play the game normally. Since completing this scenario will be difficult, you may wish to save the game at this point to avoid having to repeat the opening story section.}
{LGK Bortes Abduction Title}
{Abduction!}
{LGK Bortes Abduction Text}
{One day your camp is surprised by a party of raiders from the Merkit tribe. You flee for your life, but your bride Borte is carried off into captivity. The Merkits pursue you but you are able to hide out on the holy mountain Burkan Kaldun. 

You pray to the mountain for guidance, and eventually decide that you will rescue Borte. You send word to your allies Togril and Jamuka and they send large forces to assist you.

To rescue Borte you must capture the Merkit town of Ulan Ude by turn {0}, or be known as a coward who could not protect his women.}
{LGK Borte Rescued Title}
{Reunited}
{LGK Borte Rescued Text}
{Congratulations, your have rescued Borte and looted the Merkit's camp. Borte has been gone eight months and is now pregnant. Although the paternity is questionable, your accept the child as your own, and when he is born name him Jochi.}
{LGK Event Jamuka 2 Title}
{Jamuka Again}
{LGK Event Jamuka 2 Text}
{Your old friend Jamuka has now become leader of the Jadaran tribe. Happy to be reunited with him, and grateful for his help in rescuing Borte, you join your camp with his.

However, you are not a man who accepts a subordinate status easily, and eventually grow tired of being treated as an underling. You separate your camp from Jamuka's. Many of his own people choose to come with you. This has led to bad blood and fighting with your sworn brother.}
{LGK Event Own Man Title}
{Your Own Man}
{LGK Event Own Man Text}
{You are now a proven warrior and leader with a considerable following. The income from your royal estate has been increased to reflect support from your tribe, and many have joined your camp increasing its population. Borte's people the Olkhonut are also now yours to command.

However, you have many enemies for one still young. The Merkits still remember how your father abducted your mother, your sworn brother Jamuka is your rival as the rising man amongst the Mongols. Then there are the Tatars who killed your father.}
{LGK Avenge Your Father Mission Title}
{Avenge Your Father}
{LGK Avengue your Father Mission Text}
{You recall how your father was poisoned by the Tatars when, as demanded by tradition, he stopped  to eat with a group of them he happened across.

Togril has sent word that he will make war on the Tatars, and demands your support.

You must take the settlement of Tatar by turn {0} or risk Togril's wrath.}
{LGK Tartar Captured Title}
{Booty}
{LGK Tartar Captured Text}
{The Tartars are the wealthiest people on the steppe thanks to their proximity to China. You capture much booty from them. Your treasury is boosted by the portion you keep for your share, and your generosity to your men increases your authority.}
{LGK Young Khan Title}
{A Young Khan}
{LGK Young Khan Text}
{Following your successes in battle, your Khamag tribe appoints you as their Khan. With your immediate tribe united, you can now set about uniting all the peoples of the steppe. With a single Khan to rule over them, perhaps the constant violence, horse stealing and kidnapping of women can be ended.

Your personal authority has increased.}
{LGK Mission Naimans Title}
{Attack the Naimans}
{LGK Mission Naiman Text}
{Your adoptive father Togril has long had bad relations with the Naiman tribe to the west. He asks for your assistance against them. You feel duty bound to help.

Attack the Naiman by turn {0} or suffer a drop in authority.}
{LGK Event Togril Betraual Title}
{Togril Betrayal}
{LGK Event Togril Betrayal Text}
{Your adoptive father Togril has grown old and frail. His son is jealous of you, and fears that Togril may make you his heir. He convinces Togril that you are dangerous and not to be trusted, and Togril reluctantly goes along with it. You are now at war with the Keraits.}
{LGK Mission Genghis Khan Title}
{Become Genghis Khan}
{LGK Mission Genghis Khans Text}
{You are now undoubted the most powerful man on the Steppe, and only a few minor tribes refuse to recognize your authority. The time has come to assert your rule, and claim the title Genghis Khan.

Return to your capital and issue a Great Kurultai edict.}
{LGK Mission Attack Xi Xia Title}
{Attack Xi Xia}
{LGK Mission Attack Xi Xia Text}
{You have succeeded in uniting the peoples of the steppe, but without a constant flow of booty, the warriors will grow restless and begin fighting amongst themselves again.

It is suggested that you attack the kingdom of Xi Xia to the South. They are rich and powerful, but the previous ruler was recently murdered by his cousin who has not yet consolidated his rule.

This mission is not compulsory.}
{LGK Mission Attack Kara Khitans Title}
{The Silk Road}
{LGK Mission Attack Kara Khitans Text}
{The king of the Qocha Uyghurs has sent an emissary and begs to become your vassal.

He tells you that the new king of the Kara Khitan has been mistreating Muslim merchants on the Silk Road and that this has caused much trouble and disruption to trade.

Controlling the Silk Road would bring you much power and wealth, so you agree to take care of the problem.

Capture Balasagan by turn {0}.
}
{LGK Mission Atteck Jin Title}
{Attack Jin}
{LGK Mission Attack Jin Text}
{Your fane has spread far and wide, even as far as the court of the Altan Khan, the Emperor of Jin and ruler of Northern China. He has sent an emissary demanding that you recognize him as the Son of Heaven and your overlord.

You recall the stories of how your great grandfather was lured to the Jin court to submit, and betrayed and killed there. You are determined to be avenged.

China is the richest and most populous region in the world. To successfully complete this campaign you need to capture it. However, war against the Jin will be long and hard. So gather your allies and plan it well.}
{LGK Event Merchants Seized Title}
{Merchants Seized}
{LGK Event Merchants Seized Text}
{You recently dispatched a merchant caravan  to the realm of Khwarazem in the West. Ostensibly to open friendly trading relations, but also because reports from merchants are a rich source of intelligence about rival states.

However, your caravan has been seized. You send an emissary to demand its release.}
{LGK Mission Atttack Khwarazem Title}
{Attack Khwarazem}
{LGK Mission Atttack Khwarazem Text}
{Your emissaries to Khwarazem have returned, minus their heads. This is a mighty insult, which cannot go unavenged.

The empire of Khwarazem is very powerful, but most of it territory is newly conquered and full of unrest. Also the Shah is feuding with his mother and cannot rely on the loyalty of his army. There are many walled cities so take many siege engines, and employ terror tactics to encourage the cities to surrender.

Destroy Khwarazem completely.}
{LGK Mission Xi Xia Betrayal Title}
{Xi Xia Betrayal}
{LGK Mission Xi Xia Betraual Text}
{The Emperor of Xi Xia sees that your armies are engaged far and wide, and believes  that you are vulnerable. He has seized the opportunity to renounce his alliance with you and declared war.

There is nothing worse than betrayal and disloyalty, so your response must be swift and extreme.

Destroy Xi Xia.}
{LGK Event Khasar Title}
{Khasar}
{LGK Event Khasar Text}
{Your younger brother Khasar has come of age, and is available to lead your armies. Khasar is actually his nickname earned on account of his bravery and skill with a bow.}
{LGK Event Borochu Title}
{Borochu}
{LGK Event Borochu Text}
{One time when you were young, a thief stole all your family's horses. You chased after him on the one remaining horse. On the trail you came across a boy who pointed out the way the thief and taken, and came with you to help recover them in a chase that took three days.

Full grown he has now joined you as a trusted companion, and can be used to lead your armies.}
{LGK Event Jelme Title}
{Jelme}
{LGK Event Jelme Text}
{Jelme was given to you as a child, but was deemed too young and sent home. Later his father again presented him to serve you. He has become one of your most trusted companions and is now available as a character in his own right. You may use him to lead your armies or govern your settlements.}
{LGK Event Jebe Title}
{Jebe}
{LGK Event Jebe Text}
{During one battle you were shot in the neck by an arrow. Afterwards you asked who among the enemy had done this. A man came forward expecting to be executed, but you spared his life and gave him the nickname Jebe meaning arrow. He quickly revealed himself to be a brilliant and daring general, whom some rate as the best cavalry commander of all time.

He his now available to lead your armies.}
{LGK Event Subutai Title}
{Subutai}
{LGK Event Subutai Text}
{Subutai is the younger brother of Jelme. During his teen years he was appointed as your door guard, and his loyalty and intelligence quickly became apparent. With access to your tent he was able to learn quickly from your greatest captains, and quickly proved his skill in the early missions he was given.

He his now available to lead your armies.}
{LGK Event Muqali Title}
{Muqali}
{LGK Event Muqali Text}
{Originally presented to you as a teenage slave, Muqali quickly became one of your most trusted and able servants. You promoted him to the rank of commander of a thousand, and he distinguished himself in battle. He has now been promoted to the rank of general and is available to lead your armies.}
{LGK Event Tayichiud Title}
{Tayichiud}
{LGK Event Tayichiud Text}
{The Tayichiud clan are your kinsmen who abandoned you on the steppe all those years ago, and who later held you prisoner for a while. They fear your growing power and worry that you thirst for revenge. They are now moving against you openly, and gethering the support of the other tribes.}
