{HPTitle Contents}
{Contents}
{HPTitle Not Found}
{Page Not Found}
{HPHead See Also}
{See Also}
{HPText Not Found}
{The requested page could not be found.}
{HPTitle Basics}
{The Basics}
{HPHead Info Button}
{How To Get Help}
{HPText Info Button}
{Use the info button in the top right corner to show help for the current game area, or press the F1 key.}
{HPHead Desktop Camera}
{Basic Operations}
{HPText Desktop Camera}
{Move the camera around by using the keyboard or drag the map by holding the left mouse button and dragging. Rotate by holding down the middle or right button. The indicator in the top right shows the direction you are facing, with straight up indicating north.}
{HPText Desktop Selection }
{Click on a banner to select an army or garrison, click on a name tab to select a settlement.}
{HPLink Moving Units}
{About Moving Units}
{HPHead Turns}
{Turns}
{HPText Turns}
{The game is played in a series of turns. During your turn, you plot the movement of your armies, and set construction and other tasks to be performed. When you press the "End Turn" button, your armies will begin to march, together with those of all the other players. }
{HPHead Touch Camera}
{Basic Operations}
{HPText Touch Camera}
{Move around the map by dragging with one or two fingers. Pinch to zoom in and out, and rotate with two fingers to change the view direction. The indicator in the top right shows the direction you are facing, with straight up indicating north.}
{HPText Touch Selection}
{Tap a banner to select an army or garrison, tap a name tab to select a settlement.}
{HPTitle Unit Stacks}
{Unit Stacks}
{HPHead Unit Stacks}
{Unit Stacks}
{HPText Unit Stacks Desktop}
{Clicking a banner selects a stack of units. Stacks may contain both military units and civilian settlers. Up to eight units are allowed in a stack or city garrison. The tiles at the bottom of the screen show  the units in the stack. }
{HPText Unit Stacks Touch}
{Touching a banner selects a stack of units. Stacks may contain both military units and civilian settlers. Up to eight units are allowed in a stack or city garrison. The tiles at the bottom of the screen show  the units in the stack. }
{HPHead Moving Stacks}
{Moving Unit Stacks}
{HPText Moving Stacks Desktop}
{Right click on the hex you wish to move to. If the move is possible the path to be taken will appear. When you end the turn, the units will begin marching. If the distance is long, several turns will be required to complete it. Cancel the move with the button at the bottom of the screen.}
{HPText Moving Stacks Desktop 2}
{Hold the shift key while right clicking to make the stack move to the location after reaching its previously ordered one. This lets you set waypoints if you need to go via a particular route.}
{HPText Moving Stacks Touch}
{Touch and hold on the hex you wish to move to until the movement arrows appear. When you end the turn, the units will begin marching. If the distance is long, several turns will be required to complete it. Cancel the move with the button at the bottom of the screen.}
{HPHead Arranging Stacks}
{Arranging Unit Stacks}
{HPText Arranging Stacks Desktop}
{You can change the formation and facing of the units in the stack using the buttons below the tiles. If the stack has a move ordered, any change to facing will only affect its facing at its final destination.}
{HPText Arranging Stacks Desktop 2}
{If the stack has multiple lines of units, the colored lines above the tiles show which units are in each line. You can drag unit tiles into another line to rearrange the formation. The left hand side is the front line.}
{HPText Arranging Stacks Touch}
{You can change the formation and facing of the units in the stack using the buttons below the tiles. If the stack has a move ordered, any change to facing will only affect its facing at its final destination.}
{HPText Arranging Stacks Touch 2}
{If the stack has multiple lines of units, the colored lines above the tiles show which units are in each line. You can drag unit tiles into another line to rearrange the formation. The left hand side is the front line.}
{HPLink Leaders}
{Characters}
{HPLink Unit Cards}
{Unit Cards}
{HPTitle Unit Cards}
{Unit Cards}
{HPHead Unit Cards Introduction}
{Introduction}
{HPText Unit Cards1}
{The tiles you see at the bottom of the screen shown when a stack is selected, represent the military and civilian settler units in that stack.}
{HPText Unit Cards2}
{The symbol on the card shows how the unit is armed, and the color shows the quality (red = nobles, green = militia etc). If it has upgraded armor, this is shown by a colored shield in the top left, and the top right shows the unit's experience level.}
{HPText Unit Cards3}
{The two bars at the bottom represent the unit's strength and readiness. The green bar is strength, and the orange is readiness. Readiness will be reduced by moving and fighting, but will increase again if the unit is left to rested by not moving for a few turns.}
{HPText Unit Cards4}
{If a unit has taken losses, these will be gradually replenished when the unit is in the territory of a friendly settlement that can recruit units from that movement pool. For instance, if a unit is a trained army unit, it can be replenished in the territory of any settlement with a barracks.}
{HPText Unit Cards5}
{The symbols above the bars show the unit's battle plan for its current orders.}
{HPTitle Naval Units}
{Naval Units}
{HPHead Naval Basics}
{Basics}
{HPText Naval Basics 1}
{You can recruit naval units from boatyard or shipyard buildings that you have constructed. Naval units can move along navigable rivers and on the seas. They can carry land units, block sea trade routes, battle other naval units, and assist in land battles on the shore.}
{HPText Naval Basics 2}
{Since naval units are large, only four are allowed in a stack. Some exceptionally large ships take up a whole hex by themselves.}
{HPHead Naval Movement}
{Movement}
{HPText Naval Movement 1}
{Where naval units can move depends on their type. Those designed for use on rivers, can only move on rivers, and coastal sea hexes. Small sailing ships can move on sea hexes and river hexes. Large sailing ships can only move on the sea. Ships can only move across sea and ocean hexes when the relevant technological advances have been made.}
{HPText Naval Movement 2}
{There are two types of rivers, navigable, and unnavigable. Naval units may not move along the latter, as they are too narrow, shallow or rocky for any large boats or ships. The rocks along their length show which rivers are unnavigable.}
{HPHead Carry Land Units}
{Carrying Land Units}
{HPText Carry Land Units 1}
{Most naval units can carry one land unit. Smaller ships and boats can only carry infantry, while larger ones can carry cavalry, chariot and artillery units. The very large ships can carry multiple units.}
{HPText Carry Land Units 2}
{To embark onto ships, the land units must start adjacent to them. Select the land units to embark, and order them to move to the hex containing the ships. They will embark immediately.}
{HPText Carry Land Units 3}
{To disembark, simple order the fleet to a land hex. The land units will immediately disembark on an adjacent land hex, with orders to move to the target hex. If you select individual land unit cards, only these will disembark.}
{HPLink Naval Units}
{Naval Units}
{HPTitle Settlement Basics}
{Settlement Basics}
{HPHead Settlement Introduction}
{Introduction}
{HPText Settlement Introduction 1}
{This is where you manage your settlements, You can construct buildings inside or outside the settlement, alter the surrounding landscape, and recruit units. Use the buttons at the top of the screen to select between the different activities.}
{HPText Settlement Introduction 2}
{When you first open the settlement, you are in the "Land Improvement" mode where you can clear forests, build farms and roads, and construct buildings outside of the settlement. Close any open panel to return to this mode.}
{HPHead Settlement Stats}
{Settlement Information}
{HPText Settlement TopStats}
{The area at the top of the screen shows your settlement population, growth rate, food production and income. It also shows unrest amongst the peasants and nobles. Pressing one of the buttons will open the details panel with more information.}
{HPText Settlement BottomStats}
{The area at the bottom shows the number of turns of food stockpiled, and for herder factions. the number of animal flocks. You can also set the settlement to be automatically managed by the computer here. The tiny colored icons on the left show the proportion of the population engaged in various activities. }
{HPText Settlement Name}
{Tap or click on the settlement name at the top of the screen to change it.}
{HPLink Recruitment}
{About Recruitment}
{HPLink Internal Construction}
{About Building Construction}
{HPLink Terrain Improvement}
{About Land Improvement}
{HPLink Settlement Details}
{Settlement Details}
{HPLink Settlement Basics}
{Settlement Basics}
{HPTitle Recruitment}
{Recruitment}
{HPHead Recruitment Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Recruitment Intro}
{Here you recruit military units and civilian settlers. The units you recruit are available for use immediately, allowing a large force to be raised when you need it. The small tiles represent the units available. Click or tap a tile to open a panel showing its description, and a button to recruit it.}
{HPHead Recruitment Pools}
{Recruitment Pools}
{HPText Recruitment Pools}
{Units are grouped into recruitment pools, depending on the type of people who will form them. The dots to the right show how many units are available in each pool. There are often several types of unit available, and you can recruit any mix of types up to the limit available in that pool.}
{HPText Recruitment Pools 2}
{The pools regenerate slowly over time as new men come of age and are trained. Emptying all the pools at once may leave you vulnerable in the future.}
{HPHead Recruitment Location}
{Recruitment Location}
{HPText Recruitment Location}
{Units may either be recruited in the settlement garrison, or outside one of the gates. Use the arrows at the bottom of the panel to change the location. There is a limit to the number of units allowed in each location, and units already there are shown in gray.}
{HPHead Recruitment Stats}
{Stats}
{HPText Recruitment Stats}
{The unit description shows the cost to recruit a unit, and the cost each turn to maintain it. At the bottom are numbers for its combat attack and defense skill, armor, morale, and movement rate (hexes per turn). Use the "Details" button to reveal further details about a unit, and any special abilities it may have.}
{HPHead Cancel Recruitment}
{Cancel Recruitment}
{HPText Cancel Recruitment}
{You can cancel the recruitment of any unit recruited this turn. Just drag it out of the panel, or right click if using a mouse.}
{HPTitle Internal Construction}
{Building Construction}
{HPHead Construction Intro}
{Basics}
{HPText Construction Intro}
{Most buildings are constructed inside a settlement. The various available buildings are shown by the tiles, and grouped into categories. Select a tile to show the building description and for a button to begin construction.}
{HPText Construction Intro 2}
{The description shows both the cost to construct a building, and the cost to maintain it each turn.}
{HPHead Construction Queue}
{Construction Queue}
{HPText Construction Queue}
{Buildings take several turns to construct, and only one can be worked on at a time. The lower part of the panel shows the queue of buildings under construction, with the number of turns required shown on the tile. You can drag the tiles around to reorder the queue, or drag tiles out of the panel to cancel construction.}
{HPText Construction Queue 2}
{The cost of construction is not deducted until a building reaches the head of the queue.}
{HPHead Temples and Schools}
{Temples and Schools}
{HPText Temples and Schools}
{There are several types of these available, but only one type may be constructed in each settlement. If you want to construct a different type, you will need to destroy the first one.}
{HPHead Upgrade Settlement}
{Upgrading the Settlement}
{HPText Upgrade Settlement}
{When a settlement is large enough, you may upgrade it by constructing the "City" building from the top row of the panel. This will allow it to contain more buildings and people. The number of buildings currently allowed in the settlement is shown by the buildings in the skyline below the construction queue. Defenses are not included in this limit.}
{HPHead Existing Buildings}
{Existing Buildings}
{HPText Existing Buildings}
{Use the" Constructed" tab at the top of the panel to see what buildings have already been constructed. Tap or click a tile to see a description, and for an option to destroy it.}
{HPHead Number of Buildings}
{Number of Buildings Allowed}
{HPText Number of Buildings 1}
{Each settlement has space for one palace, one temple or school, and a limited number of other buildings. The icons below the construction queue show how many buildings you have space for, and which spaces are occupied. Upgrading the settlement to a larger size increase the number of buildings that can be constructed.}
{HPText Number of Buildings 2}
{Red and blue colored buildings are upgrades to existing buildings, and don't count towards the limit.}
{HPTitle Terrain Improvement}
{Land Improvement}
{HPHead LandImprovement Intro}
{Basics}
{HPText LandImprovement Intro}
{When no other panel is open, you can improve the land around your settlements, construct buildings in the countryside, and build roads. Some actions require certain technology to carry them out. Use the buttons (which may be at the top or bottom of the screen depending on screen resolution) to switch between the various improvement modes.}
{HPText LandImprovement Intro 2}
{The tiles on the map show which hexes may be improved. Tap or click on the tile to schedule it to be improved. A number will appear showing the number of turns to completion. Tap or click it again to cancel the improvement.}
{HPText LandImprovement Intro 3}
{Each category may be worked on independently, but each will require labor that will no longer be available for farming, slightly reducing food production and tax income.}
{HPHead Farm Improvements}
{Farms}
{HPText Farm Improvements}
{Turns a suitable hex into a farm or terrace that may be used for food production. Farms may also be improved to irrigated farms. Constructing a farm on the edge of your territory claims that hex for the settlement. Constructing farms has no monetary cost.}
{HPHead Clearance Improvements}
{Clearing}
{HPText Clearance Improvements}
{Clear hexes to allow a farm or road to be built, or to be used for animal grazing. Clearing hexes has no monetary cost.}
{HPHead Road Improvements}
{Roads}
{HPText Road Improvements}
{Roads allow faster movement of troops. Roads can be built out from city gates or from existing roads. Roads may be built in nearby hexes outside of a settlement's territory, but not in the territory of another settlement.  Building roads has no monetary cost.}
{HPHead External Buildings}
{External Buildings}
{HPText External Buildings}
{Where suitable sites are available, some building types can be constructed outside of the settlement; for example ports, mines and mountain shrines. Since suitable sites are required, most settlements will only be able to construct one or two external buildings, and some may not be able to construct any at all.}
{HPText External Buildings 2}
{Tap or click the building tile to open a panel showing its details, and the cost to construct it.}
{HPTitle Settlement Details}
{Settlement Details}
{HPHead Settlement Details Intro}
{Basics}
{HPText Settlement Details}
{This panel gives a detailed explanation of the factors affecting your settlement. The four tabs give detailed breakdowns of the factors affecting income, unrest, food production, and labor allocation. Examining these details carefully will give clues about how to improve settlement performance, and are particularly important to pay attention to where unrest is high.}
{HPLink Food Production}
{Food Production}
{HPTitle Food Production}
{Food Production}
{HPHead Food Production}
{Food Production}
{HPText Food Production}
{A settlement can produce food from four sources: animal or fish resources on the map. food produced inside the settlement from gardens or domestic animals, farming and animal grazing. Food can also be imported by trade.}
{HPText Agriculture}
{One or two units of population are assigned to work each farm or terrace hex within the settlement's territory. The amount of food grown will depend on the hex type, the amount of population allocated, and modifiers due to technology. Population is automatically distributed to maximize output.}
{HPText Grazing}
{Some societies are pastoral, depending on their animals for food, rather practicing agriculture. This requires more land than farming, but fewer people, and allows settlement on land too dry to grow crops. Each unit of population can look after animals grazing in two hexes, and each hex can support one or two flocks depending on its type. One unit of food is produced for each two grazed flocks.}
{HPText Grazing 2}
{If your chosen faction is an agricultural one, you will not be able to use flocks. If your faction is a pastoral one, you won't be able to create farms until you develop agriculture.}
{HPTitle Unrest}
{Unrest}
{HPHeading Unrest Basics}
{Nobles and Peasants}
{HPText Unrest 1}
{Unrest occurs when your people are unhappy. Different things make different people unhappy, so there are two types of unrest, "peasant unrest" and "noble unrest". As a ruler, you will have to balance the needs of the two groups.}
{HPText Unrest 2}
{The final unrest for each group is composed of three elements, happiness, dissatisfaction, and suppression. The first two are opposed and can cancel each other out. Suppression is a measure of your ability to suppress dissent by use of force or intimidation, and is mostly based on the presence of military forces in the region. }
{HPHeading Unrest Effects}
{Unrest Effects}
{HPText Unrest Effects 1}
{Unrest below 60% has no effect, but remember that random events or fluctuations in local factors can cause it to increase unexpectedly. If unrest goes above this then several bad effects may occur. The income you can collect from the settlement may be reduced, you may not be able to recruit units from some recruitment pools, and the settlement or nearby armies are more likely to join a rebellion. Bandits appearing nearby are a sign of peasant unrest.}
{HPText Unrest Effects 2}
{If unrest gets above 90% there's an increasing risk of the settlement and nearby armies starting a new rebellion.}
{HPHeading Unrest Causes}
{Causes of Unrest}
{HPText Unrest Causes 1}
{Both noble and peasant unrest can be caused by unpopular edicts, military service, natural disasters and random events. }
{HPText Unrest Causes 2}
{Local factors can be a major cause of dissatisfaction. They represent factors such as ancient grudges, particularly outspoken individuals or local traditions of independence, as well as minor local events such as fights, insults etc. There is nothing you can do about local factors, except to create happiness or suppression to counter them. They vary randomly over time, with a slight tendency to increase as the game progresses.}
{HPText Unrest Causes 3}
{Peasant unrest will also increase if there is a shortage of food, overcrowding or they are continually asked to perform labor service constructing buildings or land improvements.  Dissatisfaction due to overcrowding can be reduced by expanding the settlement to a city or large city, and a few turns of not making any improvements will reduce dissatisfaction due to labor service.}
{HPText Unrest Causes 4}
{Nobles are inherently independent, and dislike having anyone over them. They will try to assert their independence (which increases their unrest value) when they sense your realm is too large for you to control, i.e. your authority rating is insufficient for the number of settlements you control. Unrest will also be higher in settlements further from your capital.}
{HPHeader Dealing With Unrest}
{Dealing With Unrest}
{HPText Dealing With Unrest 1}
{The best way to do deal with unrest, is either to address the root causes of dissatisfaction, or to counter it by constructing buildings or issuing edicts to create happiness. }
{HPText Dealing With Unrest 2}
{In the short term though, a character with a high Ren(virtue) rating can be sent to the settlement, or military forces placed in the garrison or nearby. Note though, that noble units will not suppress noble unrest, and militia or tribal units will not suppress peasant unrest.}
{HPLink Unrest}
{Unrest}
{HPTitle Rebellions}
{Rebellions}
{HPHeading Noble Rebelllions}
{Noble Rebellions}
{HPText Noble Rebellions}
{Noble rebellions represent an attempt by one or more prominent noblemen to either overthrow the current faction leader, or to break away and form their own state. The nobles form their own breakaway faction that is automatically at war with you. }
{HPHeading Peasant Rebellions}
{Peasant Rebellions}
{HPText Peasant Rebellions}
{These are revolts by the peasant class against their common enemy, the aristocracy (which includes you). A peasant rebellion is not aimed at any one particular faction, rather they hate all equally. This makes them very dangerous, as once a rebellion begins, armies and settlements from any player may defect to it.}
{HPHeading Army Defections}
{Defecting Armies}
{HPText Army Defections 1}
{Rebellions are particularly dangerous, because an army close to a rebel stack may defect to the rebels. An army consisting of mainly nobles may defect to a noble rebellion, and an army of mainly militia or tribesmen may defect to a peasant rebellion. The chances of defection depend on the composition of the stack, and the unrest level in the settlement (if in friendly territory). Imperial Guard and Regular Army units have no tendency to join with either sort of rebellion.}
{HPText Army Defections 2}
{If a garrison stack defects, then so does the settlement it occupies.}
{HPLink Rebellions}
{Noble and Peasant Rebellions}
{HPTitle Trade}
{Trade}
{HPHeading Trade Basics}
{Introduction}
{HPText Trade Basics 1}
{Certain buildings and resources on the map provide abstract trade items that can be traded to other settlements generating income. There are a number of different types, including copper, ceramics, silk and jade. They are not directly represented in the game, although sometimes there are benefits to having certain items available at a settlement. To begin trading with nearby settlements, construct a "bazaar" building. Upgrading this building will increase the value of trade generated, and the length of trade routes allowed. }
{HPText Trade Basics 2}
{The revenue generated trading with a particular settlement depends on the goods traded, and the population of the partner settlement. Since you cannot trade an item to a place that already produces it, try to establish production centers for each item, rather than trying to produce them everywhere.}
{HPHeading Trade Routes}
{Trade Routes}
{HPText Trade Routes 1}
{Trade routes are automatically established to nearby settlements when a bazaar is established. They are shown on the map (when zoomed out) as moving dotted lines in the color of the owning player. The rate of movement indicates the amount of trade flowing.}
{HPText Trade Routes 2}
{Trade routes can't run through forests, so sometimes it will be necessary to clear the trees to establish a route. Trade routes are also blocked by the presence of enemy or hostile armies. Establish a Fraternal Harmony agreement with another player to stop them blocking your routes.}
{HPHeading Water Trade}
{Water Bourne Trade}
{HPText Water Trade}
{Trade may also be conducted along navigable rivers, and across the sea, however it is only possible if both settlements have a "Quay" building. Moving goods by water is more efficient, so water borne trade is more valuable, and can be conducted over longer distances.}
{HPHeading Internal Trade}
{Internal Trade}
{HPText Internal Trade}
{Some buildings that generate tradable items (e.g. ceramics or silk) also generate income from internal trade. Within a settlement. It's not necessary to establish a bazaar to receive this, but doing so will increase the value of the internal trade.}
{HPHeading Foreign Trade}
{Foreign Trade}
{HPText Foreign Trade}
{So long as you are not at war, your settlements may also establish trade routes to settlements owned by other players. The value of some trade items is increased if you have a higher culture rating, and decreased if you have a lower one.}
{HPHeading Caravansaries}
{Caravansaries}
{HPText Caravansaries}
{The length of direct trade routes is limited, but by establishing a Caravansary building, a settlement can re-export goods that is importing. A chain of one or more caravansaries can be used to move goods over long distance, for instance from a remote location to major cities.}
{HPLink Trade}
{Trade}
{HPTitle Execution Phase}
{Order Execution Phase}
{HPHead Execution Phase Intro}
{Basics}
{HPText Execution Phase Intro}
{Once you have given your orders, and ended your turn, the orders of all players are executed simultaneously. Units march to their assigned positions, and enemy forces that meet fight battles.}
{HPText Execution Phase Intro 2D}
{The rate at which time progresses depends on the camera height, so if you zoom in close men will move at a realistic rate, whereas if you zoom out they will move faster. Using the "fast forward" button forces everything to maximum speed. The space bar toggles between fast and normal modes.}
{HPText Execution Phase Intro 2T}
{The rate at which time progresses depends on the camera height, so if you zoom in close men will move at a realistic rate, whereas if you zoom out they will move faster. Using the "fast forward" button, forces everything to maximum speed, but may result in jerky camera motion. }
{HPText Execution Phase Intro 2P}
{The pause button will pause unit movement and combat, but still allow you to move around the map and examine what is happening.}
{HPHead Execution Phase Battles}
{Battles}
{HPText Execution Phase Battles}
{If two forces clash, a graphic for the battle will appear on the bar at the bottom, showing the sides and strengths. Click or tap the graphic to select the battle and zoom to its location. The battle plays out under computer control, with units acting according to the battle plan you set for them.}
{HPTitle Technology}
{Technology and Culture}
{HPHead Technology Intro}
{Basics}
{HPText Technology Intro}
{The Technology and Culture screen lets you guide the social and technological development of your society. There are four different areas that develop simultaneously. Use the tabs at the top of the screen to show the developments available in each area, and to choose which to work on. You may choose one item from each area.  }
{HPText Technology Power}
{Power contains developments that are guided or enforced by the emperor, king or government. These include large scale construction and military reforms.}
{HPText Technology Craft}
{Craft contains developments relating to your society's ability to make things. Developments here represent the accumulation of know how and experience among your artisans.}
{HPText Technology Thought}
{Thought is the area that deals with abstract ideas. It contains developments for philosophy, religion and the arts.}
{HPText Technology Knowledge}
{Knowledge contains developments relating to the natural world, science, and discoveries of specific techniques.}
{HPHead Technology Developments}
{Developments}
{HPText Technology Developments}
{Each potential development has a tile representing it, showing an icon for the development, the number of turns required to complete it, and a smaller icon for the type of development. Click or tap a tile to show details of the development and to allow it to be selected as the item in that area. The display at the bottom shows the current item selected in each area.}
{HPText Technology Developments 2}
{At the beginning only a few primitive developments may be selected. The connecting lines from the bottom of the tile show which items it will unlock. The differently colored tiles on the right of the panel are developments from other areas that must be completed before certain items in this area can be unlocked.}
{HPHead Technology Progress}
{Progress}
{HPText Technology Progress}
{In general the rate of development is the same for all players, so small nations develop at the same rate as large ones. However, the rate of progress in certain areas or for specific types of development can be affected by the faction you control, edicts you issue, or buildings you construct. If there is modification to the progress rate of an entire area, it is shown at the top in the tab for that area. If there is modification to a specific item, it is indicated by a colored tab on the tile. Green indicates faster than usual progress, red slower. However, in all cases the number shown on the tile is the actual number of turns that will be required to complete the development.}
{HPLink Culture and Authority}
{About Culture and Authority}
{HPTitle Edicts}
{Edicts}
{HPHead Edicts Intro}
{The Basics}
{HPText Edicts Intro}
{Edicts are laws and regulations that you issue to change the functioning of your state. They cover a wide range of measures from raising new taxes, to military reforms. They are also used to keep the balance between the central government, the nobility and the peasants.}
{HPText Edicts 1}
{Each Edict has its own pros and cons. Some have long term benefits, while causing short term unrest, as changing laws always upsets someone. Others may have a cost per turn, or offer a short term gain in return for long term disadvantages. The panel on the left side shows the edicts that you can issue. Click on one to see details, and choose whether or not to issue it.}
{HPText Edicts 2}
{The panel on the right shows edicts that have already been issued. Selecting one shows details, and may give an option to cancel it. Cancelling an edict too soon after issuing it will make you look weak and indecisive, reducing your authority.}
{HPText Edicts 3}
{Some edicts cannot be cancelled, or are in effect for a specific period of time.}
{HPTitle Culture and Authority}
{Culture and Authority}
{HPHead Culture and Authority}
{Culture and Authority}
{HPText Culture and Authority}
{These are two important values that reflect the development of your civilization, and how large it can grow. They are shown in the display in the bottom left of the map screen. They mainly increase from developments in Technology and Culture, as your people develop a shared culture, and become used to the idea of living in a large state or empire.}
{HPHead Authority}
{Authority}
{HPText Authority 1}
{Authority is the quantity that governs the relations between you and the nobles of your realm. These have a natural desire to rebel and govern independently, which your authority discourages. In practical terms your Authority rating is the number of settlements you can keep under control. If you have more settlements than your Authority rating, the noble unrest in each one will be greatly increased, possibly leading to rebellion.}
{HPText Authority 2}
{Authority comes from developments in Technology and Culture, from Edicts and from military success. It can be lost by cancelling Edicts, military defeats, and is temporarily reduced when a new leader takes the throne.}
{HPHead Culture}
{Culture}
{HPText Culture 1}
{Your Culture rating represents your soft power, and the degree to which your people have a common identity and desire to be part of a common nation. It reduces unrest amongst both nobles and peasants alike. }
{HPText Culture 2}
{Culture mostly comes from development in Technology and Culture, although there are Edicts that increase it too. Unlike Authority, it generally only increases.}
{HPLink Technology}
{Technology and Culture}
{HPLink Edicts}
{Edicts}
{HPTitle Leaders}
{Characters}
{HPHead Leaders}
{Characters}
{HPText Leaders 1}
{Characters represent the great people of history, and should be used to lead your most important armies, or govern your most difficult cities. One is your faction leader (king or emperor), another is his heir. As your kingdom develops you will acquire other characters representing the leading lights of your nation.}
{HPText Leaders 2}
{Each character is attached to a military unit (his bodyguard) and can be moved around by moving this unit. If a stack has a character present, his portrait will be shown in the bottom left when it is selected.}
{HPText Leaders 3}
{Each character has two important attributes that reflect his capabilities. These may rise and fall as he ages or to reflect events in the game.}
{HPHead Leaders Qi}
{Qi}
{HPText Leaders Qi}
{Qi (energy) is shown by the stars below the portrait or next to the army banner. Qi increases the combat effectiveness of any stack the character commands.}
{HPHead Leaders De}
{Ren}
{HPText Leaders De}
{Ren (virtue) is shown by the lightning symbols. A character's Ren increases the battle morale of the army he leads, and reduces unrest in any settlement where he is garrisoned. }
{HPHead Succession}
{Succession}
{HPText Succession}
{Your faction leader and heir are special in that they will never rebel against you. When the faction leader dies, the heir will become the new faction leader, and in due course a new heir will be appointed. If your faction leader dies without an heir (who has maybe died or not yet been appointed), then this will be a dangerous time for your kingdom and widespread rebellion may occur.}
{HPTitle Diplomacy}
{Diplomacy}
{HPHead Diplomacy Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Diplomacy Intro}
{The diplomacy systems allows you to interact with the other players you have met. You can make various sorts of treaties and deals with them. Open the Diplomacy display using the button on the right hand side.}
{HPHead Diplomacy Info}
{Display}
{HPText Diplomacy Display1}
{The displays lists all the other players that you have encountered so far, and their allies (including vassals and overlords) and enemies. The colors on each bar show that player's relation to you. Selecting a bar will show some basic information about the state of your relations with them, and will usually allow you to open a direct negotiation. You can also initiate a negotiation by double clicking/tapping a player's bar.}
{HPText Diplomacy Display2}
{The status column of the display also shows which other player (if any) a given player recognizes as their overlord or as the rightful emperor. An overlord is indicated by showing the overlord's symbol with a black decoration, and an emperor is shown with a gold decoration. Find the players who recognize you as emperor or overlord by scanning this column for you own symbol, or see the Relations tab of the Player Status screen.}
{HPLink Diplomacy}
{Diplomacy Display}
{HPTitle Vassals}
{Vassals, Overlords and Emperors}
{HPHead Vassals Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Vassals Intro 1}
{During the game, players may sometimes submit to other players and become their vassals. The other player is then their overlord. Generally this will be to avoid destruction by the overlord, or to gain protection from a third party. The vassal continues to play the game, but is subject to certain restrictions. The overlord cannot attack his vassal, but gains a number of benefits. However, a vassal can rebel at any time.}
{HPHead Vassals Obligations}
{Obligations of Vassals}
{HPText Vassals Obligations 1}
{When a player becomes a vassal, they lose a great deal of their diplomatic freedom. They may not attack any players that their overlord has a peace, non-aggression or defensive alliance with, nor any of their overlord's other vassals. They must always go to war with any player their overlord is at war with, and make peace with any that their overlord makes peace with.}
{HPText Vassals Obligations 2}
{A vassal can only win the game by a cultural or points victory (although this is unlikely), and losses some authority. A vassal does not necessarily have to pay tribute, but a regular payment may well be part of the agreement.}
{HPText Vassals Obligations 3}
{If a vassal's overlord is the vassal of another player, all the restrictions also apply to the overlord's overlord.}
{HPHead Overlords Obligations}
{Obligations and Privileges of Overlords}
{HPText Overlords Obligations 1}
{A player's authority is increased for having vassals, but the main benefit of accepting a vassal, is that the vassal's population counts as your own for purposes of Domination and Son of Heaven victory conditions, but their settlements do not count towards your authority limit. Therefore accepting vassals allow you to increase your empire to a size much greater than could be supported with your authority rating. The risk is that your vassals could rebel if they think you look weak.}
{HPText Overlords Obligations 2}
{An overlord may never attack their vassal, and is expected to defend them if they are attacked. }
{HPHead About Emperors}
{Recognizing an Emperor}
{HPText About Emperors 1}
{Accepting another player as an overlord is accepting a real position of subordination, while recognizing another player as Emperor is more of a nominal submission, and involves only minor sacrifices.}
{HPText About Emperors 2}
{A player who recognizes another as Emperor suffers a small loss of authority, and may not be recognized as Emperor themselves. A player may only recognize one player as Emperor. A vassal automatically recognizes either their overlord, or  whomever their overlord recognizes as Emperor.}
{HPText About Emperors 3}
{A player recognized as Emperor gains some authority, and may count the population of all those recognizing them towards a Son of Heaven victory.}
{HPLink Vassals}
{Vassals, Overlords and Emperors}
{HPTitle Negotiations}
{Negotiations}
{HPHead Negotiations Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Negotiations Intro 1}
{The Negotiation Screen is where you get down to business, and make deals with your fellow rulers. You put together a proposal by selecting what you will offer, and what you want in return. When satisfied, hit the "Submit Proposal" button, to see whether they agree or not. }
{HPText Negotiations Intro 2}
{Whether they agree, will depend on a number of factors, how much they like you, how much they trust you, and your position in the game. You can increase the amount other players like you by making agreements that are favorable to them, or giving them gifts. Trust is earned by keeping your agreements, and lost by breaking them. Breaking an agreement reduces your trust from all the other players, not just the one who you broke the agreement with.}
{HPText Negotiations Intro 3}
{You will also receive offers from other players. You must chose whether to accept or reject them.}
{HPHead Negotiations Offers}
{Offers}
{HPText Negotiations Offers}
{Use the panel on the left to select the items you will offer to the other party. They are organized by type, select a heading to show the items under it. You may offer money, information, treaties or make declarations. If you select "Become Vassal" from the left side, you are offering to become the other party's vassal. If you select "Recognize Emperor", you are offering to recognize them as Emperor.}
{HPHead Negotiations Demands}
{Demands}
{HPText Negotiations Demands}
{On the right side, are the items that you want to receive from the other player. If you select "Become Vassal" from the right side, you are demanding that they become your vassal. If you select "Recognize Emperor", you are demanding that they recognize you as Emperor.}
{HPHead Negotiations Declarations}
{Declarations}
{HPText Negotiations Declarations}
{Declarations are a unilateral change in relations that you make. In this case the offer merely serves to inform the other player. You may not include declarations with other items. You can declare war with a declaration, which is also the way for a vassal to revolt against their overlord.}
{HPHead Negotiations Treaties}
{Treaties}
{HPText Negotiations Treaties}
{There are various types of treaties you can make. Generally they are bilateral, that is both sides agree to the same thing. All the treaty types are listed under offers on the left side.}
{HPLink Negotiations}
{Negotiations}
{HPTitle Treaties}
{Treaty Types}
{HPHead Non Aggression Pacts}
{Fraternal Harmony}
{HPText Non Aggression Pacts}
{In this agreement, both sides agree to recognize each other as brothers and to exist together in peaceful harmony. They agree not to attack one another, nor to block each other's trade routes, or to block farming if passing through each other's territory. The agreement remains in force until one side breaks it by declaring war, or the agreed time limit is reached.}
{HPHead Defensive Alliances}
{Defensive Alliance}
{HPText Defensive Alliances}
{In a defensive alliance, each side agrees to declare war against any power that attacks the other. However, if the other player declares war on another power, there is no obligation to assist. In addition all the terms of a Fraternal Harmony Pact are in force. The treaty lasts until one side breaks it by not declaring war when required to do so.}
{HPHead Peace Treaties}
{Peace Treaty}
{HPText Peace Treaties}
{When a Peace Treaties is made, the two sides agree not to make war on each other for the given time, nor to block each other's trade routes, or to block each other's farming. In essence, it is the same as a Fraternal Harmony agreement, but with a shorter time span. When a Peace Treaty expires, the two parties do not return to a state of war, but either party is free to attack the other again, without it being regarded as a breach of trust.}
{HPLink Treaties}
{Treaty Types}
{HPTitle Controls and Hotkeys}
{Controls and Hot Keys}
{HPHead HK Camera Controls}
{Camera Controls}
{HPHead HK Common Actions}
{Common Actions}
{HPText Pan Camera Mouse}
{Drag with left mouse button}
{HPText Pan Camera Keys}
{WASD or Arrow Keys}
{HPText Pan Camera}
{Pan Camera}
{HPText Rotate Camera Mouse}
{Drag with right or center button}
{HPText Rotate Camera Keys}
{None}
{HPText Rotate Camera}
{Rotate Camera}
{HPText Zoon Camera Mouse}
{Scroll Wheel}
{HPText Zoon Camera Keys}
{Page Up, Page Down, Z and X}
{HPText Zoom Camera}
{Zoom In or Out}
{HPHead HK Unit Stacks}
{Unit Stack Actions}
{HPText Left Click Mouse}
{Left Click}
{HPText Select Banner}
{Select an army or settlement garrison by clicking on its banner. Select a unit within a stack by clicking again on the unit's banner. Open the management screen for a settlement by left clicking or tapping on its name tab.}
{HPText Right Click Mouse}
{Right Click}
{HPText Move Banner}
{Order the selected stack to move.}
{HPText Double Click Mouse}
{Double Click}
{HPText Open Settlement}
{Open the settlement management screen by double clicking its garrison banner, or single clicking on its name tab.}
{HPText Shift Key}
{Shift Key}
{HPText Set Waypoint}
{Hold shift while right clicking to order a stack to move to a location after reaching its previous one (i.e. to set a waypoint)}
{HPText Keyname Enter}
{Enter}
{HPText Action End Turn}
{End Turn}
{HPText Keyname F1}
{F1}
{HPText Action Help}
{Show Help Screen}
{HPText Keyname F12}
{F12}
{HPText Keyname F11}
{F11}
{HPText Action Mute Sound}
{Mute Sound}
{HPText Keyname Esc}
{Esc}
{HPText Action Escape}
{Close screen or open Load / Save menu}
{HPText Keyname Space}
{Space Bar}
{HPText Action Space}
{Toggle between fast and normal speed during battle phase. Show or hide the Advisor text.}
{HPHead HK Display}
{Display}
{HPText Keyname Alt G}
{Alt + G}
{HPText Action Toggle Grid}
{Toggle Hex Grid On / Off}
{HPText Keyname Alt B}
{Alt + B}
{HPText Action Toggle Banners}
{Toggle Banners On / Off}
{HPText Keyname Ctrl S}
{Ctrl + S}
{HPText Keyname Ctrl L}
{Ctrl + L}
{HPText Action Save Game}
{Save Game}
{HPText Action Load Game}
{Load Game}
{HPText KeyName F5}
{F5}
{HPText KeyName F6}
{F6}
{HPText KeyName F7}
{F7}
{HPText KeyName F8}
{F8}
{HPText KeyName F9}
{F9}
{HPText KeyName F10}
{F10}
{HPText Action Diplomacy Screen}
{Diplomacy Screen}
{HPText Action Technology Screen}
{Technology Screen}
{HPText Action Edicts Screen}
{Edicts Screen}
{HPText Action Status Screen}
{Status Screen}
{HPText Action Finance Screen}
{Finance Screen}
{HPText Action Charts Screen}
{Charts Screen}
{HPText KeyName B}
{B}
{HPText KeyName R}
{R}
{HPText Action Build}
{Open Construction Panel}
{HPText Action Recruit}
{Open Recruitment Panel}
{HPText Alt T}
{Alt + T}
{HPText Hide Trade Routes}
{Hide Trade Routes}
{HP Link Controls and Hot Keys}
{Controls and Hot Keys}
{HPTitle Battle Plans}
{Battle Plans}
{HPHead Battle Plans Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Battle Plans Intro 1}
{During your turn you may assign a battle plans to units, that determines how it will behave in battle. By default it is set to attack, which is fine for most situations, but for important battles you may want to fine tune your tactics. If you set a defensive plan (ambush, defend, reserve or withdraw) for all units in a stack, it will stop when encountering enemy, rather than initiating a battle.}
{HPText Battle Plans Intro 2}
{To set a battle plan, use the button below the unit stack, then select the plan from the pop up. If you have any units selected in the stack, the plan will be set for just those units, otherwise for the whole stack.}
{HPText Battle Plans Intro 3}
{The plans are listed below in order of aggressiveness. In siege assaults, units with the most aggressive plans will be selected preferentially for assaulting breaches.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Charge}
{Charge}
{HPText Battle Plans Charge}
{Make an immediate all out melee attack. This plan is useful to force units with missile weapons to attack in hand to hand combat, or if you want to attack quickly before the enemy can withdraw, or receive reinforcements. It's a plan that should be used with care.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Attack}
{Attack}
{HPText Battle Plans Attack}
{Attack the enemy using either missiles or hand to hand combat. If other units are perform harass or outflank plans, then delay the attack to allow those plans to take effect.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Harass}
{Harass}
{HPText Battle Plans Harass}
{Move forwards to threaten the enemy, and engage them with missile fire (if applicable) but only enter combat if the odds are favorable. Fall back if seriously threatened, or under heavy fire. This plan is most useful for mobile missile units.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Outflank}
{Outflank}
{HPText Battle Plans Outflank}
{Attempt to work around the enemy's flank, before launching an attack. This is useful if you outnumber the enemy, or they are in a favorable position.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Ambush}
{Ambush}
{HPText Battle Plans Ambush}
{Wait in position concealed from the enemy, until there is an opportunity to attack them in flank or rear, or otherwise make a highly favorable attack. This plan is only effective if in forest terrain that can provide concealment. Otherwise it is the same as defend.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Defend}
{Defend}
{HPText Battle Plans Defend}
{Hold a defensive position, only attack enemy that come close to the position. This is useful to keep a defensive line, or to avoid units moving into unfavorable terrain.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Reserve}
{Reserve}
{HPText Battle Plans Reserve}
{Hold position. Only move to engage enemy that are engaging or threatening other friendly units. Can be useful to combat outflanking enemy, to maintain a second line of missile units behind a defensive line, or to keep a leader's bodyguard from fighting unless absolutely necessary.}
{HPHead Battle Plans Withdraw}
{Withdraw}
{HPText Battle Plans Withdraw}
{Avoid combat. If the battle is going badly, withdraw. It isn't possible for a whole stack to withdraw without engaging, so you'll need to pick one or more units to act as a rearguard by given them a different battle plan (e.g. defend).}
{HPLink Battle Plans}
{Battle Plans}
{HPTitle Battle Basics}
{Battle Basics}
{HPHeading Battle Intro}
{When Battles Occur}
{HPText Battles Intro 1}
{Battles occur when an army moves into a hex adjacent to an enemy army (unless it is already moving away), or when two armies simultaneously move into adjacent hexes. When a battle begins, the armies arrange themselves according to their battle plans, and fight the battle until one side is destroyed, or their morale breaks and they run away.}
{HPText Battles Intro 2}
{Unit stacks that are adjacent to a battle will generally be included in it, unless moving away, and stacks that arrive while the battle is in progress can join the battle as reinforcements.}
{HPText Battles Intro 3}
{Battles proceed entirely under computer control. Players may not control units directly, although they may of course indirectly affect the course of the battle by the battle plans and formations they have previously set.}
{HPText Battles Intro 4}
{Battles that are currently taking place will be shown along the bottom of the screen. Clicking one will move the camera to its location, and bring up a display showing the number of men left on each side.}
{HPHeading Battle Resolution}
{Battle Resolution}
{HPText Battle Resolution 1}
{Battles are resolved on a soldier by soldier basis. When a soldier fires a missile, or takes a swing at an enemy, the chance of scoring a kill is computed using a large number of factors. These include the weapons used, the troop types, the combat skill, experience and readiness of each combatants, the terrain, and of course the defender's armor. The Qi rating of a stack's general also boosts the attack of his men, and many technology advancements will improve effectiveness in combat. In melee, attacking from the rear is of course much more effective.}
{HPText Battle Resolution 2}
{As units fight and take casualties, their morale will gradually reduce, and if it falls low enough, they will break and run away. Initial morale depends mainly on the troop type of a unit and the Ren rating of their commanding general. Morale is mainly reduced by casualties suffered, but may also be affected by being attacked by certain troop types or weapons.}
{HPLink Battle Basics}
{Battle Basics}
{HPTitle Post Battle}
{After the Battle}
{HPHeading Post Battle}
{After the Battle}
{HPText Post Battle 1}
{Generally battles continue, until all of one side's units have been destroyed or have run away. The loser's units will retreat to a nearby hex, while the winner's will regroup and may continue moving, possibly engaging in further battles.}
{HPText Post Battle 2}
{The winner of a battle may recover some of the their casualties (these soldiers were wounded not killed). How many wounded soldiers can be recovered depends on what medical advancements the player has. All the losers casualties are lost permanently.}
{HPText Post Battle 3}
{A battle that has been going on too long will automatically be ended as a draw as both sides mutually disengage. This happens when each side is unable or unwilling to attack the other effectively.}
{HPHeading Experience}
{Experience Gain}
{HPText Experience}
{Units that have been involved in battle, will gain in experience, depending on their involvement. With enough experience they will gain chevrons on their unit card, which increase their effectiveness. Both winners and losers can gain experience.}
{HPHeading Battle Reports}
{Battle Reports}
{HPText Battle Reports}
{After a battle, a report will be added to your message list, giving a detailed breakdown of how each unit fared. Units that gained an experience chevron are shown with a yellow splash. A red splash highlights a destroyed unit. Note that casualties recovered after a battle are not shown in the report.}
{HPLink Post Battle}
{After the Battle}
{HPTitle Battle Unit Types}
{Unit Roles In Battle}
{HPHeading Battle Unit Infantry}
{Infantry}
{HPText Battle Unit Infantry}
{Your foot soldiers are the mainstay of most armies. They are particularly useful for siege battles, and suffer little or no penalty for operating in difficult terrain, unless they are armed with long weapons. Infantry can be vulnerable to cavalry or chariots, unless armed with halberds or long spears, and are also vulnerable to artillery if they are in close order. }
{HPHeading Battle Unit Chariots}
{Chariots}
{HPText Battle Unit Chariots 1}
{The chariot was a significant advance in military technology. Chariot mounted warriors can move faster, wear heavier armor and carry more ammunition than soldiers on foot. The height of their fighting platform gives them another edge over infantry, and taken together all their advantages outweigh their small numbers. }
{HPText Battle Unit Chariots 2}
{Chariots move faster than infantry in open terrain, but slower in difficult terrain and cannot enter forests. If forced to fight in forests, marshes or on steep slopes, they are very vulnerable and suffer large combat penalties.}
{HPHeading Battle Unit Cavalry}
{Cavalry}
{HPText Battle Unit Cavalry}
{Cavalry are a cheaper and more efficient way of using horses in battle than chariots. They move faster, suffer lower terrain penalties, and have a combat bonus when fighting chariots. They also receive a combat bonus against infantry and a special charge attack when they contact. The latter is particularly effective when the cavalry are armed with long spears. }
{HPHeading Battle Unit Artillery}
{Artillery}
{HPText Battle Unit Artillery 1}
{The main use for artillery is to knock down walls and destroy towers in siege battles. Smaller types of engine may not be able to damage the largest walls, but can always attack towers.}
{HPText Battle Unit Artillery 2}
{Artillery can also be useful in field battles. However, since they cannot move, they will need to be positioned carefully to be useful. Stone throwers can do a lot of damage, but are inaccurate and can sometimes hit your own troops. Bolt shooters are useful for long range sniping at enemy engines, or attacking cavalry or heavily armored enemy.}
{HPText Battle Unit Artillery 3}
{When an artillery unit is ordered to move, it is packed up onto carts, and cannot fight in battle. Artillery is thus much easier to use when not moving. If you want to move and fight, make sure not to include the artillery in the move order if you want them to fight in the battle.}
{HPLink Units In Battle}
{Unit Types In Battle}
{HPTitle Siege Assaults}
{Siege Assault Battles}
{HPHeading Siege Assault Intro}
{Introduction}
{HPText Siege Assault Intro 1}
{If you attack a settlement, then a siege assault battle will occur. The attacker's siege engines and archers will attack the settlement walls and towers, trying to create a breach in the wall, or force a gate open. They will then attack the breaches or gates and attempt to force their way in. Defending units are allocated to protect a breach when an enemy unit comes near. Units defending a gate or breach never run away.}
{HPText Siege Assault Intro 2}
{The settlement surrenders, and the battle ends when an attacking unit reaches a breach or open gate, and their is no defending unit available to defend it. When the city surrenders, all defending units that started in the settlement are destroyed.}
{HPHeading Settlement Defenses}
{Settlement Defenses}
{HPText Settlement Defenses}
{If a settlement has a wall, it will also have some towers that can fire on the attackers. If missile units are garrisoned in the settlement, they are assumed to be garrisoning the towers, boosting their attack rate, and changing the projectiles used from simple arrows, to whatever they are armed with. A strong garrison will combine some missile units to fire on attackers, with some strong defensive melee troops to defend breaches.}
{HPHeading Prolonged Sieges}
{Prolonged Sieges}
{HPText Prolonged Sieges 1}
{The attacker must capture the settlement within the time limit allowed for battles, which is usually not possible if the settlement is well defended. If the settlement is not captured, the siege continues, and the attacker can try again in the next turn.}
{HPText Prolonged Sieges 2}
{Any damage caused to the defenses is remembered from turn to turn. Two damaged pieces (wall, gate or tower) are automatically repaired each turn, even when under attack.}
{HPHeading Unwalled Settlements}
{Unwalled Settlements}
{HPText Unwalled Settlements}
{If a settlement has no walls, then the attackers must force their way in along one of the four entry roads. Defending units will defend these as if defending a wall breach, but without protective walls, they will be very vulnerable to missile fire.}
{HPLink Siege Assaults}
{Siege Assaults}
